<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quatuor novissma: Or, Meditations upon the four last things, delivered in four common-place discourses: by Thomas Longland ...</title>
            <author>Longland, Thomas, 1629 or 30-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1633_2</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50796709</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50796709</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 205:E1633[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Quatuor novissma: Or, Meditations upon the four last things, delivered in four common-place discourses: by Thomas Longland ...</title>
                  <author>Longland, Thomas, 1629 or 30-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 128, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Maxey for J. Rothwell, at the Fountain in Goldsmiths-Row, Cheapside.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each discourse has caption title; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 8."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heaven --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hell --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quatuor Noviſsima:</hi> OR, MEDITATIONS UPON <hi>The Four Laſt Things,</hi> DELIVERED In four COMMON-PLACE DISCOURSES:</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Thomas Longland</hi> M.A. and Fellow of S. JOHNS College in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 32.29.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Haec ſpirituatis eſt exercitii ſumma, haec forma ſtudii spiritualis, ut ſapientèr disponamus praeſentia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, recogitemus in amaritudine animae noſtrae praeterita, futura quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolicitè provideamus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern. in Solen.</hi> Pet. <hi>&amp;</hi> Paul. <hi>Ser. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Maxey</hi> for <hi>J. Rothwell,</hi> at the Fountain in Goldſmiths-Row, Cheapſide. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND AND LEARNED, <hi>Anthony Tuckney</hi> D. D. <hi>Regius Profeſſor;</hi> And Maſter of S. JOHNS College in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Reverend</hi> SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe few Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, which (next to their being <hi>Gods Sacred
<pb facs="tcp:170181:3"/>Truth</hi>) derive <hi>all their Worth,</hi> from your vouchſafing an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of them, had not ſeen the <hi>light,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you had caſt a <hi>ſmiling Aſpect</hi> upon them and their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.<note n="⸪" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.7.</note> The grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Rivers acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg their Homage, by ſending their Streams to the <hi>Ocean</hi> from whence they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>Dumb Creatures
<pb facs="tcp:170181:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>teach me to ſpeak, and thankfully to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That next to God, you are <hi>One,</hi> to whom I owe what I have or can do. You have been the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit, through which he hath conveyed much good to my outward, many Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to my inward Man. I deſire to praiſe him, to teſtifie my Thanks to you, by Devoting theſe
<pb facs="tcp:170181:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Meditations to <hi>His Honour,</hi> your <hi>Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> and Peruſing. Let others commend their Patrons; deſire of Praiſe, implieth weakneſs in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; your <hi>Brighter Name</hi> ſtands not in need of ſuch a <hi>ſhadow</hi> as mens Applauſe, to make it more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in the world. <hi>Native Worth</hi> is ever more reſpected, than <hi>Adventitious Glory:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170181:4"/>Yet excuſe me, if I ſay you are one who in theſe <hi>laſt</hi> dayes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to Meditate of the <hi>laſt</hi> things, who in theſe <hi>worſt</hi> dayes, put not the <hi>evil day</hi> far from you, or him who preſents it to your view. Your Acceptance of theſe <hi>Papers,</hi> doth make them more welcome to thoſe who are look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sion-ward,</hi> and doth encourage him
<pb facs="tcp:170181:5"/>in what may promote his own or their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney thither: who is</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>St. Johns Col: Camb.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 30. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours, In all Obligations Chriſtian and Civil, <hi>Thomas Longland.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SUch thou art, or my deſire is thou ſhouldſt be, into whoſe hands theſe Papers are fallen. I did once think to have ſaved my ſelf the pains in writing, though not thee the trouble in the peruſal of an Epiſtle. But being moſt privy to my own thoughts in the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Diſcourſes to the World, and alſo the beſt Judge of my own Intentions in their compoſure, I thought it
<pb facs="tcp:170181:6"/>convenient to acquaint thee, That theſe Meditations were the Reſult of ſome vacant hours; the occaſion of which was <hi>(what I pray may be their effect upon thee;)</hi> namely, A deſire ſo to <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> my dayes, that I might apply my heart to wiſdome: Which afterwards I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver in a <hi>Learned Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> yet contrary to my firſt thoughts. I ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to communicate them unto others; not doubting but they may <hi>(through Gods Bleſſing)</hi> be uſeful in the World; and may in ſome meaſure teſtifie my deſire to acknowledge my Obligations
<pb facs="tcp:170181:6"/>to him, who hath <hi>Honoured me</hi> in the Acceptance of them to his Patronage. Theſe, <hi>and ſuch like,</hi> were the Reaſons of adventuring this ſmall Eſſay of my Studies to vulgar view. If any <hi>ambiguity</hi> in the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions be taken notice of, know, The ſafeſt Interpretation was my intention: If any <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity</hi> appeareth in the Phraſe, conſider, They were not delivered, much leſs ſuited <hi>Ad Populum,</hi> To the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar:</hi> And ſhould I have altered the phraſe, (in <hi>ſome</hi> places) the ſenſe would have been inverted. If any thing elſe want an <hi>Apologie,</hi> let
<pb facs="tcp:170181:7"/>thy Charity finde an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.12.</note> Remember thy Tongue is thy <hi>Glory,</hi> and is better uſed in Praying for, than Cenſaring of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cambridge <date>March <hi>30. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine, To promote thy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Welfare, <hi>T. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170181:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 9.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>It is appointed to men once to die, but after this the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſiderations of death to living men,<note place="margin">Charron of Wiſdom, lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> though uſually moſt unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; yet are the moſt profitable to promote the Duty of Preparation thereunto: for which purpoſe I have made choiſe of theſe words. And becauſe I will not build without a Foundation, leſt I erect a totter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Structure, I wil firſt ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the ſcope of theſe words, and then deduce a Propoſition, which ſhall be the <hi>Baſis</hi> of my future Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170181:8"/>
            <p>Theſe words (as a Learned man notes) are alledged by the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paraeus in locum.</note> as an Argument to evince, or reaſon to prove, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> neither could, nor ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer oftner then once, which is clear, if we conſult the precedent and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent words of the Text. But it being not my intention to ſpeak to them as they ſtand in relation to the Context, but as they make an intire Propoſition; I ſhall not be ſolicitous after any inquiry of their relative connexion; but as they are in <hi>Theſi.</hi> they are the declaration of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Heaven concerning our lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end: <hi>Statutum eſt, &amp;c, It is appointed to men once to die, but after this the Judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to them in order,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Death.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Judgment.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170181:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Of DEATH.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> FRom the Firſt, they ſuggeſt to our Meditations this Doctrine, <hi>That Death is inevitable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſhort, yet <hi>ſure Truth,</hi> as we ſhall ſee in the ſequel of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>Were it not that the daily ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of mortalitie, which we ſee, the deep groans of dying men,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Serm. de Fid. &amp; leg. Naturali. <hi>Immortalia ne ſperes: monet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum quae rapit hora diem.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. lib. 4. Od. 7.</note> which <hi>eccho</hi> again, which was the uſual Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation of one, to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, That he was a man.</hi> I ſay, If theſe did not convince us, of the truth of this Doctrine; I might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to thoſe ſudden fits, and fainting diſtempers, the moſt healthful bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doth ſometimes perceive in it ſelf. To the courſe of Nature, which ſhewes us, as the longeſt day hath its cloſure in the <hi>night,</hi> even ſo the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt life muſt have its period by death.</p>
               <p>But as I do believe there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us ſuch an <hi>Epicure,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170181:9"/>not a life to come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death; ſo I in charity hope there is not ſuch an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> as doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he ſhall not die. I will paſſe this therefore, and proceed to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the nature of death, which I ſhall endeavour in the reſolution of theſe Queſtions:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Quid ſit?</hi> What it is?</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Quot uplex ſit?</hi> Of how many ſorts it is?</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Quare ſit?</hi> Wherefore it is?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the Firſt. In the reſolution of this Queſtion, <hi>What death is?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a <hi>privation,</hi> I ſhall not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſeek out a poſitive definition, but ſpeak to it as it may be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Formaliter in ſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Accidentaliter ad aliud.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>What it is formally,</hi> and in it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Death is the ſeparation of life from its ſubject: Death is not only a ceſſation from action, but a <hi>negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of exiſtence: for the ſoul may in a ſwooning fit ceaſe to operate, not to animate. There may be a ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of action, where there is not a privation of its principle; but death
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170181:9"/>ſeparateth the ſoul the fountaine of vital action, from the body the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> We will view death in what it is <hi>Accidentaliter ad aliud, Accidentally</hi> and in reference to ſomthing without it ſelf. And that to
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>The Godly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>The Wicked.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To the Godly. And ſo it is <hi>a reſt from their labours.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Hom. 51. de Sanct. Mar. Boren. &amp; Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>c.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord from henceforth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works follow them,</hi> Rev. 14.13. They reſt from
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Sin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Sorrows.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Both which the holieſt of men are exerciſed with, and ſubject to, whilſt they live in the world; they labour under the former, in the latter, whilſt in this <hi>dying life.</hi> But when they dye, that which doth ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from their bodies, doth unite them cloſer unto God. Their death is the <hi>Funeral</hi> of their ſins, the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of their Graces: that which doth <hi>unpinion</hi> them of mortality, doth alſo <hi>tranſlate</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170181:10"/>them <hi>into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God.</hi> So that <hi>Death</hi> is but a <hi>change</hi> to a holy <hi>Job;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 14.14. Act. 7.60 2 Cor. 5.10</note> a <hi>ſleep</hi> to a bleſſed <hi>Steven;</hi> a <hi>diſſolution of the earthly houſe</hi> to a holy <hi>Paul,</hi> whilſt by it he accounteth, not to be <hi>found naked, but to be cloathed upon with his houſe</hi> which is from heaven; to have mortality <hi>ſwallowed</hi> up of life, and by the <hi>death of his body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24</note> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his wiſht for deliverance, from the <hi>body of death.</hi> And this for the firſt, Death to the godly is a <hi>reſt</hi> from their ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is a reſt from their <hi>ſorrowes. Joſephs</hi> feet ſhal no longer be detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſtocks neither ſhal he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the <hi>iron</hi> which <hi>entred into his ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Nor any of the Saints and holy Martyrs ſhall at all complain of the inceſſant malice of their enemies. <hi>Death</hi> ſhal give them a reſting-place; for in the grave the <hi>weary</hi> ſhall be at <hi>reſt; There the priſoners reſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they hear not the voice of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor,</hi> Job 3.17, 18 And all this ſhall not be the effect of a <hi>Stoical a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy</hi> or ſtupefactive ceſſation from ſenſe and motion: But by an <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> into <hi>real</hi> joy. That ſoul
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170181:10"/>which was before glewed unto the body, ſhal therefore be diſſolved that it may be with Chriſt, and that which whilſt it was in the world, was but at beſt a <hi>priſoner of hope</hi> ſhall then be ſet at libertie, and have eternity wherein to expatiate; in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe manſions of glory which God hath provided for ſuch whom he ſhall account worthy to be partakers of the <hi>inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri. Septu.</note> The <hi>righteous</hi> alſo <hi>are taken away from the evil to come, Iſai.</hi> 57.1. and their graves are but <hi>beds</hi> wherein they reſt in the <hi>evening</hi> of their dayes.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee, that as to live is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo to die is <hi>gain</hi> to believers, whilſt by it they reſt from <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſorrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our next work is to conſider death in its reference to the <hi>Wicked.</hi> And to them it is the beginning of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the entry of their woe. They are the men who <hi>have hope only in this life,</hi> and therefore are of <hi>all men</hi> the moſt miſerable. That <hi>death</hi> which in its intention is to put out the candle of a good mans life, doth but ſnuff it, and make it burne the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170181:11"/>brighter, whilſt their life of grace is conſummate by being ſwallowed up in a never-ending life of Glory. <hi>This</hi> ſhall cauſe the candle of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go out in a <hi>ſtench,</hi> their <hi>Sun</hi> to ſet in a <hi>cloud,</hi> their flattering day of proſperity to end in a diſmal night of <hi>black eternal horror:</hi> whilſt by it, they ſhall at once be ſeparated from their bodies, and from the preſence of God, in whoſe <hi>favour is life,</hi> and from his <hi>right hand,</hi> where are <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore.</hi> And thus I have anſwered this Queſtion, <hi>Quid ſit?</hi> What death is?</p>
               <p>Secondly. <hi>Quotuplex ſit? Of how many ſorts it is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Death</hi> in its <hi>complexe</hi> notion repreſents it ſelf under a threefold reſpect,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Serm. 56.</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Corporal.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Spiritual.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Eternal.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe three unnatural branches, ſpring from one root; to wit, <hi>Sin.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Firſt is <hi>by ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Second <hi>in ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Third <hi>for ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Firſt is competent to both, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170181:11"/>Godly, &amp; the wicked, and hath been ſpoken to already. Let us conſider a little the ſecond, <hi>Spiritual Death,</hi> and this alſo hatha double conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>A Death in ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>A Death to ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaks of the former to the believing <hi>Coloſſians, Col.</hi> 3.13 where he tells them, that they <hi>being dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, God hath quickned them together with Chriſt.</hi> And thus the wicked are ſaid to be <hi>dead whilſt they live;</hi> there being a ſeparation between God, the Author of Spiritual life; and their ſouls, the due ſubjects thereof, by reaſon of their ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.2. And this is the eſtate of every one of us until God ſaith unto us, <hi>Live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Death to ſin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secundum Spiritum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mors eſt, non credere vina quae c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, non jacere vana; quae faciebat. <hi>Auguſt. Serm. 121. de Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. more.</hi>
                  </note> And this is the eſtate of a lively Chriſtian; of one who is <hi>paſſed from death to life.</hi> This is to be dead with Chriſt; and is a teſtimony to him in whom it is, that he ſhall <hi>live with him,</hi> Rom. 6.8. This is not, as the former, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of ſin, but the gift of God; and of this death there is a twofold teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170181:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A death to the <hi>Law.</hi> That is to ſay, when we are brought by the threatnings in the Law to know that there is no ſalvation or life to be found by the Law, but in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and this I doubt not to aſſert for the meaning of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> Gal. 2.19. <hi>For I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I might live unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> A dying to the <hi>World.</hi> A de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſing all things therein, or whatſoever it counteth admirable for the excellencie of the knowledg of Chriſt. And thus to do, is to be <hi>made conformable</hi> to the death of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>But I haſte to paſſe over theſe, which though fair fruit, yet never grew on this tree; profitable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but not ariſing from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Text, ſpoken to by <hi>tranſition,</hi> rather then regular deduction from the ſubject I am upon.</p>
               <p>I proceed to conſider death in its <hi>third</hi> acception, <hi>Eternal Death.</hi> This is the <hi>in-let of Hell,</hi> the <hi>ſum of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the <hi>ſecond death,</hi> (which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is not excluded, yet not <hi>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> intended in the words) and hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170181:12"/>power over none, but ſuch as have had no part in the <hi>firſt Reſurrection.</hi> THIS is the dregs of the fury of the Lord, the Cup of his ſoreſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which requireth eternity, to drink it to the bottom. <hi>This</hi> is the <hi>gnawing worm</hi> and <hi>unquenchable fire</hi> the ſenſe whereof doth cauſe them on whom it is inflicted to <hi>meditate terror</hi> for ever. THESE are the <hi>ſparks</hi> which the wicked have <hi>kindled</hi> from the fire of their own luſts; and wherein God will cauſe them to <hi>lye down in ſorrow.</hi> THIS is that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire,</hi> who among us ſhall dwell with it? Who among us ſhall dwell with theſe <hi>everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</hi> Every one ſhal thus die <hi>for ſin,</hi> who is before dead <hi>in ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Queſtion I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, is, <hi>Quare ſit, Wherefore it is?</hi> which will be anſwered by inquiring, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ſit? Whence it is?</hi> And there is a <hi>threefold</hi> riſe of Death:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Satan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Man.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The firſt by <hi>Temptation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſecond by <hi>Conſent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The third by <hi>Infliction.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170181:13"/>
               <p n="1">1. SATAN is the <hi>grand</hi> contriver of mans deſtruction, and therefore is the <hi>Author</hi> of it, not by a <hi>Phyſical</hi> but <hi>moral</hi> cauſality. <hi>He</hi> is the <hi>Father</hi> of ſin,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Jam: 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Sin</hi> the <hi>parent</hi> of death He who is the <hi>Antient of daies</hi> tells us, the Devil is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A murderer from the beginning.</hi> And through mans cowardiſe in conſenting to ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he who at the firſt did but u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp, hath now <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the power of death:</hi> and is not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, but by <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is <hi>ſtronger then he. And</hi> bleſſed be God that the <hi>Author of Death</hi> is overcome by him who is the <hi>Prince of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.14, 15.</note> and the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> and <hi>finiſher</hi> of that faith againſt which the <hi>gates of hel ſhal not prevail</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 2. <hi>Man conſenting.</hi> This is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe of death: to prove this, ſee that remarkable place, Rom. 5.12.<note place="margin">Hic enim duo concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator et ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperator. Zeged. loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> commu.</note> 
                  <hi>As by one man ſin entered into the world &amp; Death by ſin, &amp; ſo death paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men for that all have ſinned.</hi> We were no ſooner <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> but we were <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>Death.</hi> Our firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; we in him did eat of that apple, the <hi>core</hi> whereof doth yet ſtick in our throats, and will at length choak us one by one. <hi>Sin</hi> is our own work, &amp; <hi>death is the Wages of ſin,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170181:13"/>brings me to the <hi>third</hi> cauſe, <hi>God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting.</hi> If man by his ſin ſaith he <hi>will die,</hi> God by his decree ſaith he <hi>ſhall die;</hi> ſo that man ſhal have his will though it end in his woe. If <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> will needs entaile an hereditary curſe upon his poſterity, God will ſo ratifie it by his ſupreme Act in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it ſhall never be cut off, it ſhall be <hi>inevitable,</hi> ſeeing he hath <hi>appointed for men once to die.</hi> And thus we have the reſolution of theſe three Queſtions. I ſhall only anſwer an objection, and ſo proceed to uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But <hi>is this true?</hi> It is <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to men,</hi> men indefinitely; to all men to die. <hi>What is the reaſon we read of ſome perſons who did not,</hi> of <hi>ſome who ſhall not taſte of Death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>I. Anſwer, Particular exceptions deſtroy not the verity of general rules:</hi> becauſe ſome go out of the backdoor, we doe not therefore ceaſe to ſay that the gate is the ordinary way out of the houſe; and becauſe ſome hath not <hi>ſeen</hi> death, or others ſhall not, we need not ceaſe to affirm, <hi>It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> for <hi>men once to die;</hi> for men are ſaid to <hi>die</hi> either <hi>properly,</hi> and really, or by way of <hi>aequiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency,</hi> when they ungergo a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170181:14"/>
                  <hi>Change</hi> equal with death. Thus did <hi>Enoch</hi> when he was tranſlated; <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah,</hi> when carried to heaven in a fiery Charriot, and this ſhall they undergo who ſhall be found alive when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhal come to judgment. The eſſence of Death or rather its nature, not conſiſting in <hi>cinerefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but (as I have before affirmed) in a <hi>ſeparation</hi> of life from its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which in Gods people is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a bleſſed diſ-union, of ſin from their ſoul. They are no longer ſubjects of ſin, when once veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of eternal glory.</p>
               <p>The next thing in order of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod will be to make ſome inference from what hath been ſaid, and let me premiſe this, it will be wiſdom for us to look this <hi>King of Terror</hi> in the face, and to conſider whether we are able to encounter with him or no; and what <hi>Nero</hi> did when he heard he was ſentenced by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as an enemy to the Publick Weale, to be puniſhed <hi>More majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> deſpairing to live, he tried the points of the Ponyards wherewith he had reſolved to dye, to feel their ſharpneſs, before he ſheathed them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170181:14"/>in his bowels. So it would be wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in us. by ſerious reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our frailty, to <hi>die daily,</hi> that ſo the day of our death may not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize us unawares. Storms are moſt terrible when they ſurprize us ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and without a ſhelter. Death will then be moſt unwelcome, when it overtakes us unprepared or unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to grapple with it.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now endeavor to apply this Doctrine.</p>
               <p>If this be true, <hi>That death is ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable;</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> then let us live as ſuch who are to die. Becauſe death is an evil to nature let us not haſten it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a neceſſary conſequent of our ſin: Let us endeavour, that though it ſeparate our ſouls from our bodies, yet it ſeize not on us in ſuch an eſtate, which will ſeparate both from God. Becauſe by Chriſt it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome; and proves a friend to Grace by haſting its conſummation in Glory: let us not be afraid to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with it. But alas, how few of us make this improvement of the neceſſity of death? How many by intemperance and diſorder do dig
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170181:15"/>their graves with their <hi>own</hi> teeth; How many are there whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> whileſt they are <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vino<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſepulti</hi> before their <hi>paſſing</hi>-bell hath tolled; and even whileſt their bones are <hi>full of marrow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job. 20 11.</note> their ſouls are replete with the <hi>ſins</hi> of their <hi>youth.</hi> Theſe are ſuch who put far from them the evil day; They conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not the daies of darkneſſe, neither think of them any more <hi>then</hi> (as the Prophane proverb is) <hi>Their dying day. Their inward thought is, that not</hi> only their <hi>houſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 49.11.</note> but they ſhall <hi>abide for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> not conſidering there is a God in whoſe hands are their <hi>life, breath and all</hi> their <hi>waies;</hi> that their breath is in their noſtrils, and their life ere long may be as <hi>water ſpilton the ground; that</hi> it will lay the greateſt Prince le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veld with the pooreſt Peaſant;<note place="margin">Pallida mors aequo pulſat pede pauperum tabernas Regum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> turres <hi>Hor at. lib. 1. Od. 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that Death</hi> regards not the ſcepter of a mortal Prince, nor compaſſionates the ſad eſtate of any nor will be bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to give a releaſe from natures bonds; <hi>that</hi> the <hi>grizly</hi> hand of death will cover many <hi>a naked breſt</hi> (which formerly hath been the <hi>looking-glaſſe of</hi> luſt, and pride) with a <hi>wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>-ſheet: That this which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170181:15"/>is called <hi>death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chryſoſt. Serm. de Fid. &amp; Leg Natur. Pſal. 49.14</note> ſhall <hi>cool the valour</hi> of all the <hi>hot-ſpurs</hi> in the world, who in their life time could not put up an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury without a challenge. That they ſhall <hi>roll</hi> in the duſt, who ſometimes did <hi>wallow</hi> in pleaſures, like the ſwine in the mire; when like ſheep they are <hi>laid in the grave,</hi> and death ſhall <hi>feed upon them.</hi> And how few of the heirs of life, do walk as if they were to paſs to an inheritance, but after death? whilſt ſome do either with perſecuted <hi>Elijah,</hi> or peeviſh <hi>Jonah, ſeek after death,</hi> exceedingly deſirous of the <hi>penny,</hi> but yet ſo delicate, that they they are loth to work in the <hi>heat of the day.</hi> Others of them, though they have ſet their faces towards the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and are on their journey thither, yet by the way they <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>fleſh-pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 11.5</note> and their preſent <hi>enjoyments</hi> do make them the leſſe active in the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of future <hi>felicity.</hi> God is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to caſt wormwood upon the breſts of the Creature, that he may make them the more earneſtly <hi>draw water</hi> out of the <hi>wells of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others of them conceive, God may
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170181:16"/>have honour by their lives: and therefore they are loath they ſhould be deprived of ſuch an opportunity, by their deaths. For this cauſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly the Pſalmiſt might ſay, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 102.24. <hi>O my God take me not away in the midſt of my dayes.</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Hezekiah</hi> might beg for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve after God had ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</hi> All theſe, though their intentions might plead an excuſe, yet their actions are not commendable. Yet we know, a found conſtitution is conſiſtent with ſome qualmes: and we ought to conclude, that ſtrength of grace is conſiſtent with ſome weakneſs in this particular. Gods people ceaſe not to be men by becoming Chriſtians; as they are the former they may be afraid, as the latter, they do <hi>dare to dye. Aaron</hi> upon Mount <hi>Hor</hi> can be ſtripped of his clothes,<note place="margin">Num. 20.18</note> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repining go to <hi>bed.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> wil <hi>depart in peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.29 30.</note> after his <hi>eyes have ſeen the Lords Salvation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 21.13</note> The holy Apoſtle is indifferent whether to live or dye, but if it be for the name of the Lord Jeſus he is ready not to be <hi>bound, but to dye alſo.</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170181:16"/>Thus we ſee the <hi>Shepherd of Iſrael,</hi> hath ſheep as well as Lambs in his fold; men of riper years, as well as babes in Chriſtianity. Such as dare encounter the <hi>King of terrors,</hi> as well as ſuch who are afraid at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger.</hi> in <hi>1</hi> Theſſ. <hi>4.8</hi> Morte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n mali vitant ſancti in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, quibus non tam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae hujus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritus: quam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae interitus eſt. <hi>Heidfel. Sphis Theo Phil. c. 38. p. 908.</hi>
                  </note> But all believers have this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, though few live in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it, that death to them is but a <hi>ſleep,</hi> the grave an <hi>hiding place,</hi> both a reſting from their labours: their <hi>paſſage</hi> from this <hi>vale of miſery,</hi> is but an <hi>entrance</hi> into their <hi>Maſters joy.</hi> This notwithſtanding, is not ſufficient, for a Chriſtian to know, that though he die, yet his life is <hi>hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> He muſt ſo dye, that God may be <hi>glorified</hi> by his death; the which that every one of us may do, we muſt prepare our ſelves for ſo great a <hi>change.</hi> The which preparation conſiſts in <hi>three</hi> things,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Dying unto ſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Living unto righteouſneſs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Mortification to the world.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A word to each of theſe</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Dying <hi>unto ſin.</hi> * The <hi>ſting</hi> of death is <hi>ſin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 15.56</note> he then that dyeth unto ſin, deſtroyeth death. And
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170181:17"/>frequent reflections upon death, would prove an excellent meanes hereunto. But oh! how hard is it (though we have daily Spectacles of others mortality) to live under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of our owne! we ſhould live more in heaven, if we did believe we were to die, and ſo to goe from hence. This would <hi>ſeaſon</hi> our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, lives, and check the exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy of our riſing luſts to conſider it is <hi>appointed</hi> for all men <hi>once to die,</hi> and conſequently alleviate the feare of death. For that which maketh <hi>death</hi> terrible to a <hi>conſiderative mind,</hi> is not ſo much the pain which is felt in the ſeparation of ſoul &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; (for I doubt not but men undergo more ſharp agonies (as to fenſe) in a fit of the ſtone,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. expoſ. Pſal. 116.</note> or gout, or ſuch acute diſeaſes, then at the moment of their diſſolution) nor is it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that natural abhorrency of an annihilation, or deſtruction of being. which maketh death formidable; but that which repreſents death ſitting <hi>upon a pale horſe,</hi> as deſcribed Rev. 6.8. is <hi>conſcience of ſin,</hi> and thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation unto hell following after death: but a beleever may uſe with a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170181:17"/>holy confidence, what ſometimes preſuming <hi>Agag</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Surely the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of death is paſt;</hi> and with the bleſſed Apoſtle may cloſe his eies in peace with a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.83.39.</note> 
                  <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Living unto righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mala more put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nda non eſt qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m bona vita prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerit. <hi>Auguſt. de civit: Dei lib. 1. cap. 11.</hi>
                  </note> A <hi>holy life will</hi> uſher in a <hi>happy</hi> death. This is that which doth alſo evidence our dying unto ſin, and will make us die more peaceably in our beds. We find, that they who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved moſt up amongſt the heathens to the principles of morality, were leaſt afraid to die; when thoſe who lived the moſt rudely, were moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to leave the world. <hi>Seneca,</hi> or <hi>Cate,</hi> when about to die, ſeem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ready, when a <hi>wicked Nero,</hi> whoſe conſcience told him what his mouth did utter,<note place="margin">Sueton: in vita Nero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> 
                  <hi>Vivo deformiter ac turpiter,</hi> doth depart the world with an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adeone mori miſerum eſt</hi> and encourageth himſelf to his own ruine, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170181:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>It becometh not, It becometh not thee, O</hi> Nero, <hi>to be ſo daunted, go to, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thy ſelfe.</hi> Upright <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> had not ſuch cauſe to weep, when the Prophet brought thoſe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to him,<note place="margin">Iſai. 38.1, 2</note> that he <hi>ſhould dye,</hi> and <hi>not live,</hi> ſeeing he was ſo well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for death, that he could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to God, that he had walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>in truth,</hi> and <hi>with a perfect heart,</hi> and done that which was <hi>good in his ſigh. David</hi> his father alſo, a man after <hi>Gods own heart,</hi> did thus prepare for death, and after he had ſerved his <hi>own generation, by the wil of God fell aſleep,</hi> Act. 13 35.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Mortification to the world;</hi> this will prepare us for the ſtroke of death. Thoſe things which are glewed together, are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much difficulty diſ-united; and when our affections are ſet upon earthly things, we ſhall not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think of being covered up in duſt. <hi>A bird in the hand is worth two in the buſh:</hi> and men are not eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to part with preſent <hi>delights</hi> for an expectation of <hi>future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> The man who fareth delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly every day, will not willingly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170181:18"/>hear of being <hi>meat for worms.</hi> He who is gorgeouſly arrayed (as the rich man in the Goſpel) will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſtrip himſelf to a <hi>winding-ſheet,</hi> or they that ſtretch themſelves upon <hi>their couches,</hi> will be willing to be laid in the grave.<note place="margin">Charies the Fifth.</note> 
                  <hi>Haec ſunt que fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt invitos mori,</hi> Theſe are the things <hi>which make us unwilling to die,</hi> was a ſober anſwer of that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Emperor to a magnificent Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> in the like caſe. But now a child of God, whoſe Treaſure is in Heaven, deſireth to be there himſelf alſo, leaving the world <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Apoſtle his phraſe is, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. having a <hi>deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt;</hi> who by his death doth enable his to die to earthly things, that their heart may ſoar a of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and aſpire to that place, where he their treaſure is; where their ſouls being ſequeſtred from earthly comforts, they drink no longer at the broken <hi>ciſterns</hi> of the Creature but derive all their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from him with whom their <hi>ſprings are found.</hi> Thus thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Jewels <hi>(their immortal ſouls)</hi> ſhall there ſhine in their <hi>native lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170181:19"/>where not trampled upon by <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> ſenſe, they approach to God, and are made more like to him from whom their eſſence was received. And thus much ſhall ſerve for the firſt uſe.</p>
               <p>Is <hi>Death inevitable?</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> then let this be a cordial to cheer us up <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> to ſtrengthen us <hi>againſt</hi> the loſſe of friends: we uſually ſay, <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence perforce is ſmall hearts eaſe,</hi> but yet we may make <hi>a virtue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> this <hi>neceſſity</hi> of mortality impoſed upon us, to help our patience in this particular. The wiſe heathen could comfort himſelf under the loſſe of his ſons, with this expreſſion, <hi>Scio me mortales genuiſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Laert. Diog: vita A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxag.</note> 
                  <hi>I know I have begot ſuch who are mortal.</hi> But a holy <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who knoweth that <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>appointed,</hi> and not <hi>fate</hi> impoſed, a neceſſity of Death to all, may with greater comfort ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port himſelf with a <hi>Scio Deum hoc decreviſſe;</hi> I know God hath <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> it: and with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, hold his peace</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Lord</hi> hath done it. <hi>David</hi> hath learned this leſſon exceeding well: and we ſee him take it out to the <hi>amazement</hi> of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170181:19"/>his Servants, 2 Sam. 12.21, 22, 23. even to their ſaying with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>What thing is this that thou haſt done!</hi> Much more may we comfort our ſelves, if we know they did die <hi>in the Lord:</hi> The doubt of which poſſibly might be one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the impatience, and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate grief of the aforeſaid holy man, for the death of <hi>Abſalon.</hi> Were our relations <hi>holy</hi> in their lives, they are <hi>happy</hi> after death: They have <hi>left us,</hi> we have not <hi>loſt them,</hi> but ſhall <hi>receive them,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>be received to them</hi> at the laſt day, when death ſhall be <hi>ſwallowed up into victory.</hi> 'Tis the Apoſtle his compariſon, <hi>That which thou ſoweſt is not quickned, except it die:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the body <hi>raiſed in glory,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>ſown in diſhonour,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.36 43. This is rather envy than pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to bewail the death of ſuch,<note place="margin">Charron of Wiſdom, lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their abſence from us, ſpeaks their preſence with their and our chiefeſt good. Their <hi>death</hi> is but a <hi>departure</hi> to a better life. Hence St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſpeaketh <hi>of his death</hi> for the cauſe of his <hi>bleſſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170181:20"/>Saviour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yſoſt. in Phil. 2.12.</note> and the <hi>ſervice of the Church,</hi> Phil. 2.12. doth not call for their tears, but rejoying. The ſerious belief of a <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> and this life which is <hi>to come,</hi> would be then a great ſupport, under our loſs of friends for <hi>the preſent;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.14.</note> or elſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhewed himſelf no good <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> when he maketh uſe of ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, to <hi>perſwade</hi> believers from ſorrowing, as others <hi>which have no</hi> ſuch <hi>hope.</hi> But whilſt I ſpeak for this,<note place="margin">Humanitatis vero of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia &amp; miſericordiae opera (quod &amp; alibi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuimus) per hoc non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnantur &amp;c. <hi>Bulling. in 1 Theſſ. 4.13, 14.</hi>
                  </note> I would not ſeem the leaſt to countenance <hi>or inſinuate</hi> the other extreme; I mean, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is more common in the world. Many men, who would not be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, men <hi>without hope,</hi> yet are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>without natural affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> who never think they ſhall <hi>live,</hi> till their relations <hi>die;</hi> and follow them with leſs ſorrow to their <hi>graves,</hi> then they return with laughter to their <hi>Cheſts.</hi> The which though they labour to conceal, yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170181:20"/>their neglect of <hi>Funeral Rites</hi> to their deceaſed friends, doth give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers occaſion to ſuſpect it. If you ask them a reaſon of this omiſſion, their anſwer is at hand; and becauſe you ſhall know they ſpeak not <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the book,</hi> you ſhall have the ſenſe, if not the <hi>words</hi> of the <hi>Father, O mnis iſta curatio funeris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Civit. Dei, lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>conditio ſepulturae, pompa exequiarum, magis ſunt vivorum ſolatia, quam ſubſidia mortuorum; Funeral ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mnities are rather for the comfort of the living, than the advantage of the dead; and therefore are with leſs trouble omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than coſt performed.</hi> But I could wiſh ſuch to look a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they ſhall ſoon perceive what <hi>ill uſe</hi> they make of that <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: Nec ideo tamen contemnenda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Civit. Dei, lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; abjicienda ſunt corpora defuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp;c. We muſt not therefore caſt thoſe away, from whom God hath withdrawn his breath,</hi> eſpecially thoſe bodies which have <hi>been the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans of the Holy Spirit to every good work.</hi> God will not be well pleaſed that men ſhould reſpect thoſe bodies that were <hi>the Temples of the Holy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170181:21"/>Spirit,</hi> no more than dung, which is caſt forth into the open Air: That the <hi>Stones of the Sanctuary</hi> ſhould be <hi>poured forth in the top of every ſtreet;</hi> that the <hi>precious Sons</hi> of <hi>Zion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to fine gold,</hi> ſhould be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>earthen pitchers;</hi> nor that the <hi>Body of a man</hi> ſhould be buried as the <hi>Carcaſe of a dog.</hi> The ſame God who hath commanded us, not to ſorrow, as men <hi>without hope,</hi> doth yet allow we ſhould mourn as thoſe, in whoſe hearts reſideth <hi>love.</hi> That we weep,<note place="margin">Vid. Bullin. optimè de hac re diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerentem, Dec. <hi>3.</hi> Ser. <hi>10.</hi> de Inſt. Eccleſ. <hi>Mat. 23.27, 29.</hi>
                  </note> will ſpeak us <hi>men;</hi> that in this caſe we grieve with moderation, will <hi>ſhew us Chriſtians.</hi> Indeed our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſeems to chide ſuch who did build the <hi>Tombs of the Prophets,</hi> and <hi>garniſh the Sepulchers of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> but <hi>(take notice)</hi> they were ſuch, who <hi>themſelves</hi> were as <hi>graves</hi> that did <hi>not appear,</hi> and like unto <hi>whited Sepulchers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 11.44, 47.</note> ſeeing it was not <hi>affection to the perſons of the Prophets,</hi> but <hi>reſpect</hi> to their <hi>own praiſe,</hi> which put them upon that <hi>Religious ſhew,</hi> yet <hi>Hypocritical action;</hi> they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> whilſt they pretend to <hi>do his Prophets no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170181:21"/>harm:</hi> yea, to reverence their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory <hi>after death,</hi> whom their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents not onely hated, but attempted to kill <hi>when alive.</hi> Notwithſtanding this, we finde it the practice of the <hi>Saints,</hi> to bewail the loſs of their friends, and decently to interre them. Even the <hi>Father of the faithful,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 23.2.</note> when <hi>Sarah</hi> is dead, cometh to mourn, and to weep; and with no leſs care than love, doth provide a Burial-place for her. Thus when <hi>Jacob</hi> had yielded up <hi>the ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>youngeſt Joſeph</hi> ſhews the <hi>ſtrongeſt love,</hi> and <hi>fell upon his fathers face, and wept upon him; and kiſſed him, and commandeth his ſervants the Phyſicians to embalm him,</hi> Gen. 50.1, 2. and <hi>made a mourning for his father,</hi> ver. 10. There was his <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affection</hi> as a Son, yet but <hi>ſeven dayes;</hi> there his <hi>moderation</hi> as a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Euſ. Eccleſ. hiſt. l. 1. c. 4.</note> who had hopes of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: which the <hi>Egyptians</hi> not expecting, were more extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant in their ſorrow, and mourned for him <hi>ſeventy dayes.</hi> We finde it alſo promiſed as a bleſsing to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> the Son of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that <hi>all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170181:22"/>Iſrael ſhould mourn for him,</hi> and <hi>bury</hi> him; which was performed, as to <hi>him,</hi> ſo to <hi>good Joſiah,</hi> whom the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lamented for, and <hi>all the ſinging-men and the ſinging-women spake of;</hi> and that not for once, but made it an <hi>Ordinance in Iſrael to this day,</hi> compoſing <hi>Elegies</hi> upon him: when-as wicked <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 35.25.</note> as a curſe upon him, had <hi>no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monument,</hi> but the <hi>burial of an Aſs, drawn forth, and caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the gates of Jeruſalem;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did any lament for him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Jer. 22.18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Ah Lord,</hi> or <hi>Ah his glory!</hi> Not to multiply Examples, let that of our <hi>Saviour</hi> be the laſt, who was decently interr'd, as for otehrs, ſo <hi>this account,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vid. Polan. Syntag l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> That we might be careful that our burials of the dead may be ſo comely, that it may anſwer ſomewhat the hopes we have of a Reſurrection unto life. <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> muſt not thruſt us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>certainty of Inhumanity;</hi> the former is not to be <hi>allowed,</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter muſt ever be <hi>avoided.</hi> The <hi>Medium,</hi> is, A due reſpect to thoſe <hi>after their deaths,</hi> whom we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170181:22"/>have loved <hi>in their lives:</hi> which will teſtifie to the world, they <hi>liv'd deſired,</hi> whilſt they <hi>die lamented.</hi> We in the mean time moderating our grief with this Conſideration, <hi>It is appointed unto men once to die.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170181:23"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HEB. 9.27.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But after this the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Of JUDGEMENT.</head>
               <p>HAving ſpoken of <hi>Death</hi> out of this place; I now come to ſpeak of what is after it, to wit, <hi>Judgement.</hi> Although poſſibly by Judgement may be here meant, the <hi>particular Judgement</hi> of every man; (to wit) <hi>immediately</hi> after the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Soul and Body, by Death. Yet where God hath not <hi>expreſly</hi> ſet us <hi>bounds,</hi> I ſuppoſe it is not neceſſary for us to <hi>confine</hi> our ſelves. There being therefore no ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170181:23"/>neceſſity of that reſtriction, I ſhall take my liberty to ſpeak of the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Judgement</hi> at the end of the World. In my enſuing Diſcourſe, I ſhall not attempt any Diviſion in this intire Propoſition, but deduce this Doctrine: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <q>That God hath appointed a Day in which he will Judge the World.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>expreſs words</hi> of the Apoſtle, Act. 17.31. I ſhall not heap up many Arguments, either from <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. de Laz. Con 4.</note> to prove the truth of this Propoſition; though up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on due conſideration, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from both would <hi>crowd into my thoughts.</hi> But I wave them: for I ſuppoſe my ſelf to ſpeak to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who believe, not to <hi>Infidels</hi> who <hi>may</hi> deny, at <hi>leaſt</hi> doubt, of this truth. But if I muſt needs prove it, I will go no further than that uſual expreſſion of men, to put an end to ſtrife, <hi>As God ſhall judge me.</hi> The frequency of which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170181:24"/>in mens <hi>mouthes,</hi> doth teſtifie to their <hi>faces,</hi> that God <hi>hath appointed a day wherein to judge the world.</hi> For the due underſtanding of which Truth, let theſe particulars be conſidered:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Judex, The Judge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Judicandi, The perſons to be judged.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Modus Judicii, The manner of Judgement.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Judicii Eventus, The Event of the Judgement.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we will conſider who ſhall be the Judge: We finde in Scripture this Title, <hi>The Judge of the World,</hi> attributed ſometimes to <hi>God,</hi> ſometimes to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To God,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as Gen 18.23. <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi> Eccleſ. 3.17. <hi>I ſaid in my heart, God ſhall judge the righteous and the wicked.</hi> But I ſuppoſe, thoſe and the like places, may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of Gods <hi>Providential Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> of Judgement in the World, as being the <hi>Moderator</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> thereof, and not of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170181:24"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimate and Definitive Sentence</hi> at the laſt Day:<note place="margin">Ideo antem cum diem Judicii Dci dicimus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus ultimum, vcl no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimum: quia &amp; nunc judicat, &amp; ab humani generis initio judicavit. <hi>Auguſt. de Cir. Dei, lib. 20. c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> for thus the <hi>Father judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no man, but hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all judgement unto the Son,</hi> Joh. 5.22. not but that the <hi>whole Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> do exerciſe this Work: for <hi>Opera Trinitatis ad extra ſunt indiviſa;</hi> but in a more <hi>ſingular manner Chriſt,</hi> as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and that upon <hi>theſe Accounts.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>As it is a part of his Regal Office.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>As he is</hi> iDELEGATUS DEI <hi>to this Work.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>FIRST,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>As it is a part of his Kingly Office</hi> to judge others, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Innocent, to condemn the Nocent: this is a <hi>Kingly Work.</hi> And that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath Authority to do this, is evident; for in the day of his Inauguration, when the <hi>Diadem of Glory</hi> was firſt ſet upon his head, (to wit) after his Reſurrection, he tells us, <hi>All Power is given unto him both in Heaven and in Earth:</hi> He
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170181:25"/>drunk of <hi>the Brook in the way,</hi> and <hi>here</hi> he did <hi>lift up his head.</hi> But in the <hi>laſt</hi> Day, he ſhall <hi>much more</hi> be higher than his enemies; when they who in their popular fury cried out, <hi>We have no King, but Caeſar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Videbunt ergo Judaei Deum &amp; hominem ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per regnantem quem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gande deſperaverunt morientem. <hi>Aug. de Sym. ad Catech. tract. 4. c. 8.</hi>
                  </note> and would not have him <hi>to rule over them,</hi> ſhall be <hi>brought</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and ſlain <hi>before</hi> his <hi>face.</hi> They who would not <hi>kiſs the Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter</hi> of his Grace, ſhall be bruiſed <hi>like a potters veſſel,</hi> by the <hi>iron Rod of his Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As he is DELEGATUS DEI to this Work; as God hath <hi>aſſigned, ſubſtituted, appointed him to, or committed to him</hi> the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World. See Act. 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the World in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, by that man whom he hath ordained.</hi> And ſo Rom. 2.16. <hi>God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.10. 2. Cor. 3.10.</note> And hence <hi>Gods Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> is called the <hi>Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> And thus we ſee <hi>Quis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex.</hi> SECONDLY,</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170181:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quinam Judicandi?</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Who are to be judged?</hi> The Doctrine tells us <hi>in general,</hi> the World; but more <hi>particularly</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Angels,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Men.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>FIRST,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Angels,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>The evil ones,</hi> they ſhall be judged: for therefore is it they are <hi>reſerved in everlaſting chains under darkneſs, unto the Judgement of the great day,</hi> Jude 6. This the <hi>Devils believe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 9.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and tremble</hi> becauſe of: and therefore was that cry, <hi>Art thou come to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment us before the time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But SECONDLY, <hi>Man;</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and that
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Good Men,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Evil Men.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For, ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 Corinth. 5.10. <hi>We muſt all appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> But yet this ſhall be after a diverſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: THE <hi>former,</hi> to be <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red juſt;</hi> THE <hi>latter,</hi> to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned</hi> as wicked. The former
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170181:26"/>ſhall have <hi>Confidence</hi> when he ſhall <hi>appear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt in Gen. 1. Hom. 8.</note>1 Joh. 2.28. The latter ſhall not onely be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but ſhall not <hi>ſtand in the Judgement,</hi> Pſal. 1.5.</p>
               <p>I now proceed to the third thing to be conſidered,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which is MODUS JUDICII, <hi>The manner of this Judgement.</hi> And in the right ſtating of this, theſe things muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Res Judicandae, The things judged.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Norma Judicii, The Rule of Juſtice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Aſſeſſores in Judicio, The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors in Judgement.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>FIRST, <hi>The things to be iudged.</hi> The matters to be inquired after in this <hi>great Aſſizes,</hi> at this <hi>general Audit,</hi> and what they are, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved Eccleſ. 12.14. <hi>God ſhall bring every work into Judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be evil, or whether it be good.</hi> This Judge of Heaven and Earth, is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170181:26"/>
                  <hi>Sagax animi.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt Hom. 25. de fut. Judic. tom. 6.</note> He will ſuffer no perſon, no thing to <hi>eſcape</hi> his moſt exact ſcrutiny, to <hi>avoid</hi> his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlled</hi> Sentence. He <hi>himſelf</hi> tells us, Mat. 12.36. <hi>There is not an idle word, but we ſhall give an account of it.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> goes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what further than this, Rom. 2.16. <hi>In that day when God ſhall judge,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the ſecrets of mens hearts.</hi> And if God do <hi>ſo,</hi> what is there hid, that ſhall not be made manifeſt? The <hi>Adulterer,</hi> who <hi>waiteth for the twilight, and to whom the morning is as the ſhadow of death,</hi> ſhall in that day be made manifeſt at <hi>noontide</hi> to the view of <hi>Men and Angels.</hi> And if his being known <hi>here,</hi> put him in the <hi>terrors of the ſhadow of death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 24.17</note> how <hi>terrible</hi> ſhall that day be unto him, when what he hath done <hi>in ſecret, ſhall be proclaimed upon the houſe-top?</hi> For look as the Apoſtle ſaith, Heb. 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>There is not any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſight, but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170181:27"/>all things are naked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umen. in locum.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the eyes of him, with whom we have to do: So</hi> ſhall they be to <hi>all the world</hi> at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for, <hi>there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing covered, which ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; and hid, that ſhall not be known,</hi> Matth. 10.26. The hand of Juſtice at that time, ſhall wipe away many a blot, which hath been caſt upon the people of God, their name, actions, cauſe, by the <hi>ungrateful world;</hi> and ſhall pluck off many a <hi>Mask</hi> from the face of ſuch,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c. Chryſoſt. de Pro. lib. 1.</note> who have <hi>covered hatred by deceit,</hi> and make them known in the <hi>midſt of the congregation.</hi> He ſhall then, by the <hi>Touchſtone</hi> of his Truth, diſtinguiſh <hi>gold</hi> from that which <hi>gliſters,</hi> and is not ſuch; and ſhall take every piece of <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſilver,</hi> and caſt it into a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of <hi>unquenchable fire,</hi> not to <hi>purifie,</hi> but to <hi>conſume</hi> it. In this world, <hi>Saul</hi> is ſporting in his Palace,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170181:27"/>while <hi>David</hi> is flying as a <hi>Partridge upon the Mountains; Ahab</hi> is ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf upon his Couch, whilſt righteous <hi>Naboth</hi> is breathing his laſt under a heap of ſtones; <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and his Courtiers are <hi>drinking wine in bowls,</hi> whilſt holy <hi>Eſther,</hi> with the Church of God, are <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wailing, covered in ſackcloth and aſhes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 37.6, 7. Heb. 11.37.</note> VIOLENCE <hi>covereth the wicked as a garment; their eyes ſtand out with fatneſs, they have more than heart can wiſh:</hi> whilſt the godly <hi>wander about in ſheepskins and goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented. The proud are called hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; yea, they that work wickedneſs, are exalted.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide Aug. de civ. Dei l. 20. c. 2, 3.</note> The Chaff and the Corn are mixt together in the ſame floor; the Wheat and the Tares grow together in the ſame field. But in that <hi>great and notable day of the Lord,</hi> when God ſhall appear with his <hi>fan,</hi> and <hi>throughly purge his floor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 4.1. <hi>Hic eſt qui dicitur, dies judicii.</hi> Auguſt. de civ. Dei, l. 18. c. 35.</note> he will ſeparate the <hi>precious from the vile;</hi> and <hi>all the proud, yea, all that do wickedly, ſhall be ſtubble, and that day ſhall burn them up.</hi> Then ſhall the world <hi>diſcern between the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170181:28"/>and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not,</hi> Mal. 3.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> NORMA JUDICII, <hi>The Rule of Juſtice.</hi> This alſo muſt be conſidered in Courts of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and becauſe that <hi>Lex eſt nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Judicii,</hi> we ſhall ſee that God will proceed <hi>legally</hi> alſo: for, as for heathens, who having <hi>not the law, are a law unto themſelves;</hi> if they <hi>ſin without the law, they ſhall periſh without the law,</hi> Rom. 2.12. They then ſhall be judged by this Rule, (to wit) <hi>the law of Nature.</hi> As for ſuch, <hi>Secondly,</hi> who have ſinned in <hi>the law, they ſhall be judged by the law,</hi> Rom. 2.12. and ſo that law which was <hi>ordained unto life,</hi> through their breach thereof ſhall <hi>be found to death;</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in his own perſon elſewhere, in another caſe. For ſuch then who have heard of the Moral Law, it ſhall be the Rule of their Judgement, but yet cloſer. Revel. 20.12. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſaw in a Viſion, he tells us, <hi>The dead were judged out of thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170181:28"/>things which were in the Books, &amp;c.</hi> Now there are <hi>three Books,</hi> out of which, the Dead ſhall chiefly be judged:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>The Book of Conſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>The Book of Gods Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>The Book of the Scriptures.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>Book of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> The Book ſpoken of, Rev. 20.12. which is the Book of <hi>Life;</hi> LIBER VITAE UNIUSCU jus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>(The Book of each mans Life)</hi> as one * tranſlates it;<note place="margin">Vide Aug. de civ. Dei l. 20. c. 14.</note> and that is (as he interprets it) <hi>Conſcience:</hi> into which, God ſhall infuſe a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Light, whereby all the actions of men, which have been written in it, ſhall appear, however former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may have ſeem'd raſed out by Oblivion: <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſhall then awake, however it hath been ſtifled or ſeared by counter-checks, to the dictates of an inlightned minde. Truth, though impriſoned before in unrighteouſneſs, ſhall now have its freedom to accuſe, yea, to condemn
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170181:29"/>the ſinner; and (will he nill he) ſhall ſet thoſe ſins before his eyes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.21. &amp; 51.9.</note> from which God hath not <hi>hid his face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not onely <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is the Clerk of the Aſſizes, but God, who is the great <hi>Cuſtos Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulorum,</hi> ſhall produce and prefer all the Bills of Indictment that can be brought againſt a ſinner, and reade all the Pardons which have been ſealed to a Saint, who ſtands now at Gods Tribunal, for his Trial upon Life and Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The <hi>Book of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures:</hi> This ſhall be <hi>NORMA J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICII, The Rule of Judgment.</hi> And ſo we hear the Judge himſelf ſay, Joh. 12.48. <hi>The word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him at the laſt day:</hi> And one of his chief Retinue tells us the ſame; God ſhall judge <hi>the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>according to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel delivered by me.</hi> Men ſhall be judged according to their Works, their Works according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. The wicked ſhall be judged,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170181:29"/>
                  <hi>SEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, ET PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PTER OPERA, according, and for their Works,</hi> by the Law; The godly, <hi>SEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, SED NON PROPTER OPERA, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording, but not for their Works,</hi> by the Goſpel: Which Goſpel ſhall condemn the wicked, for their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>of ſo great Salvation;</hi> and ſhall acquit the godly of their ſins againſt the Law,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Praeveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fide ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Aug. Serm. 121. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. mort.</note> by reaſon of this, that they believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the Reconciliation tendred in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE third thing</hi> in this manner of Judgement conſiderable,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is <hi>AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SESSORES IN J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DCIO,</hi> the <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> or <hi>Aſſociates</hi> in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and theſe God doth uſe out of <hi>indulgence,</hi> not <hi>indigency;</hi> to <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them,</hi> not to <hi>help him.</hi> And they are
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Holy Angels,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Glorified Saints.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Chriſt <hi>formally,</hi> the Angels <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally,</hi> the Saints <hi>declaratively,</hi> ſhall Judge the Word.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170181:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR the firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I have touched ſomewhat upon this already; onely let me adde, He is ſaid <hi>formally</hi> to Judge, who paſſeth the definitive Sentence of Life or Death, Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Condemnation upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent or Nocent; and that Chriſt with his own mouth ſhall do this, and that (as I have ſaid) as a part of his Regal Office, ſee Matth. 25.34. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right hand, &amp;c. SECOND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Holy Angels inſtrumentally</hi> or <hi>miniſterially:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for, <hi>with the ſound of a Trumpet they ſhall gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the Elect from the four winds, from the one end of heaven unto the other,</hi> Mat. 24.31. And whether or no Chriſt will uſe them as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to execute his Sentence, I ſhall not here determine; the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative</hi> ſeems evident, Mat. 13.49, 56.</p>
               <p>The Saints <hi>declaratively</hi> ſhall judge the World, 1 Cor. 6.2. <hi>Do ye not know that the ſaints ſhall judge the world?</hi> This honour then ſhall the Saints have, that they who are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170181:30"/>now trodden down as mire in the ſtreets, ſhall hereafter ſit upon the Bench with the <hi>Judge</hi> of the Earth. They ſhall judge the World: how? Not as Counſellors to this Judge; <hi>For who hath been his Counſellor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.24.</note> but <hi>declaratively?</hi> that is to ſay, either by conſenting to his Judgement, as juſt and true, as in Courts of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Judicature, they are ſaid to do, when by riſing up, or ſome ſuch ſign, they ſhew an aſſent to the Sentence, pronounced by the Judge, as the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>Court:</hi> or elſe <hi>declaratively;</hi> that is to ſay, their <hi>Faith, good Conſcience, Integriry,</hi> ſhall then ſo appear, that they ſhall make the wicked inexcuſable. And thus even in this life, <hi>Noah</hi> is ſaid by <hi>preparing an Ark,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.7.</note> to have <hi>condemned the world:</hi> And in the life to come our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.41.</note> 
                  <hi>The queen of the South ſhall riſe up in judgement with that generation which heard him,</hi> and his Goſpel, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it. And he alſo tells his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, Luk. 22.30. that they ſhall <hi>ſit on Twelve Thrones,</hi> and ſhall <hi>judge the Twelve Tribes of Iſrael;</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170181:31"/>that is to ſay, the Faith of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum.</hi> Marlorar. in loc. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 1 Cor. 4.13.</note> who were <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> yea <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant men,</hi> and yet embraced Chriſt, and were Miniſters of his Kingdom, ſhall take away all excuſe from the Iſraelites. O how ſhall the <hi>spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Beauty</hi> of a Saint (who is but in this world accounted as the <hi>filth</hi> thereof, and the off-ſcouring of all things) break forth in that day, when God ſhall make up his <hi>Jewels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Cyri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Catec. 15. p. 382.</note> even to the dazling of the eyes, and tying the tongues of thoſe, whoſe malice or detraction did ſo far hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, that they would or could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of Heaven in their lives, whilſt in this world! They ſhall then look upon them with an eye of envy, whom before they view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>ſupercilious contempt</hi> and <hi>diſdain;</hi> and with their tongues ſhall ſay, <hi>We fools counted their lives madneſs;</hi> but behold, <hi>they are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongſt the righteous.</hi> And thus much for this third Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170181:31"/>
               <p>We ſhall next ſpeak to <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICII EVENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, The Event of this general Judgement:</hi> and it is ſet down, Mat. 25.46. <hi>The wicked ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſment; but the righteous into life eternal;</hi> the former ſhall be puniſhed with <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and the glory of his power,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.9. The latter ſhall <hi>meet the Lord in the air, and ſo ſhall ever be with the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.17. It may be expected I ſhould now ſpeak ſomewhat to the <hi>LOC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICII, The Place of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And truly ſome have <hi>curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſputed,</hi> none I know of <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined</hi> this thing. Some would have it in the Valley of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat,</hi> which is ſituated betwixt the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> which is toward the Eaſt; which opinion is grounded from that of <hi>Joel</hi> 3.2. where God ſaith, He will gather <hi>thither all Nations, and plead with them there for his people:</hi> and the Argument is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from Act. 1.11. where the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel tells our Saviours Diſciples,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170181:32"/>whilſt they ſtood gazing up into heaven, that <hi>the ſame Jeſus which was taken up from them into heaven,</hi> ſhould ſo come in <hi>like manner,</hi> as they had ſeen him go <hi>into heaven.</hi> Others think it ſhall be <hi>in the Air,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grotius, Ameſius, &amp;c.</note> out of 1 Theſſ 4.7. For my part, I I deſire to be <hi>wiſe unto ſobriety;</hi> and till I better underſtand the aforeſaid places of Scripture, I ſhall believe, if God will finde <hi>a time when,</hi> he will alſo finde a <hi>place where,</hi> to judge the World.<note place="margin">Temerè de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finire non audeo, quod excogitare non valeo. <hi>Auguſt. de Civ. Dei, l. 21. c. 30.</hi>
                  </note> In the mean time, I ſhall leave it amongſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the ſecret things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God;</hi> as knowing, that thoſe things which are revealed alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to us. As for the <hi>TEMP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICII, the particular time</hi> of this <hi>general Judgement,</hi> ſome may poſſibly be inquiſitive after; and ſome, with more confidence than ſucceſs, have undertaken to define it. But I ſhould be loth to <hi>decide,</hi> what <hi>Infinite Wiſdome</hi> hath left <hi>in doubt:</hi> neither do I profeſs my ſelf to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what <hi>the Angels of heaven,</hi> nor <hi>any man</hi> doth know, <hi>but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely,</hi> Mat. 24.36. <hi>Proud deſire</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170181:32"/>of knowledge may do hurt, where <hi>humble ignorance</hi> of what God is pleaſed to conceal, doth not ſuppoſe a fault. Let me leave this therefore <hi>irreſolved,</hi> as the former, and apply what hath been already ſaid.</p>
               <p>It may inform us in the words of the Apoſtle,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Rom. 14.12. <hi>So then, every one of us ſhall give an account of himſelf to God:</hi> for therefore is this Judgement appointed, that God may exerciſe <hi>Diſtributive Juſtice</hi> in the World, by rewarding the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, puniſhing the wicked; abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the one, condemning the other: which actions ſuppoſe a ſcrutiny in mens lives. And although God who knoweth all things might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further witneſs, paſs to give Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; yet he will give the ſinner leave to <hi>plead</hi> his own Cauſe, and then out of his <hi>own mouth</hi> will <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him;</hi> or elſe ſo clear ſhall be the teſtimony of his own Conſcience, that it ſhall leave him <hi>ſpeechleſs, without excuſe.</hi> And thus the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall <hi>juſtifi:</hi> God <hi>when he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and ſhall <hi>clear</hi> him <hi>when he judgeth.</hi> Thus they who would not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170181:33"/>confeſs their ſin here, <hi>to give glory to God,</hi> ſhall (will they nill they) then confeſs it, <hi>to take ſhame unto themſelves.</hi> Neither is this account leſs ſtrict than ſure; there are no ſhifts to avoid it: we cannot blinde the eyes of this Judge with gifts, nor ſcare him with our frowns; nor appeal from <hi>his Tribunal</hi> to a <hi>higher Bench,</hi> nor hide our ſelves from his Omniſcience, or fly any where from his Preſence: His Serjeant, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> will Arreſt the proudeſt Prince, and bring him before the <hi>King of kings;</hi> where, deveſted of his Royal Pomp, he ſhall equally ſtand to receive his Doom with the meaneſt Peaſant, and ſhall there exchange <hi>his Scepter</hi> for a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> his Royal Ornaments for the <hi>White Robes of the Saints;</hi> or elſe be environed with greater ſhame. Each creature will own the Summons at that day, which the <hi>laſt Trump</hi> ſhall proclaim: <hi>The Earth ſhall give up its dead, the Sea likewiſe its;</hi> that ſo each perſon contained in them, may give an <hi>account of himſelf</hi> to God.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170181:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If God hath <hi>appointed</hi> a Day wherein to Judge the World; Then learn that, 1 Cor. 4.5. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge nothing before the time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Lord come, who will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the counſels of the heart.</hi> Let no man <hi>anticipate</hi> God, or take his Office out of his hand, by <hi>judging</hi> his brethren <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act knowledge</hi> is requiſite in a Judge;<note place="margin">Si judicas cognoſce. <hi>Sen. Med.</hi>
                  </note> but the eyes of man are too dim to judge of the actions of others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot ſee them in the heart, their Root and Fountain: for <hi>God alone</hi> ſearcheth hearts. Hence it is that holy men in this life are oft judged as hypocrites; when as on the contrary, the gliſtring gloworm of <hi>Morality,</hi> in this dark night of the world, goeth under the notion of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Integrity.</hi> Thus the <hi>righteous are condemned,</hi> and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are <hi>juſtified</hi> by thoſe, who judge <hi>after the ſight of their eyes,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>appearance,</hi> and not <hi>righteous judgement.</hi> To thoſe God doth ſpeak, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.12</note> And alſo Gods people ſay,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170181:34"/>(as to <hi>Moſes</hi> was once retorted by the Iſraelite) <hi>Who made thee a Prince,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and a Judge over us?</hi> Produce thy Commiſſion, thou that art ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in cenſuring or condemning the reſt of thy brethren: If thou haſt none, what is thy plea for this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate practice? Is it that in the Pſalmiſt;<note place="margin">Pſa. 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Our lips are our own, who is Lord over us?</hi> And therefore thy tongue <hi>walketh through the ſtreets.</hi> Haſt thou not read, that God is ready to <hi>judge both the quick and the dead?</hi> to acquit whom thou condemneſt; to condemn whom thou approveſt? Or readeſt thou not that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Jam. 5.9? Behold, the Judge ſtandeth before the door, execute not then thy malice, till God hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Sentence. It is not hatred of ſin, but <hi>deſire of revenge,</hi> which doth inflame mens tongues with a <hi>love to blame,</hi> and condemn, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and correct the faults of others; or rather as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth notably obſerve,<note place="margin">De Serm. Dom. in Mont. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi> in Mat. <hi>7.1.</hi>
                  </note> Such do <hi>labour with Pride or Envy,</hi> which cauſe their hearts to ſwell againſt the perſons and names of their brethren.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170181:34"/>
               <p>Whilſt I thus inveigh againſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another, I do not ſay, but we may ſay <hi>A ſin is a ſin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.19.</note> for the works of the fleſh are manifeſt and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fall under our cenſure. But in judging, we muſt avoid theſe <hi>three things:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> We muſt not, we may not <hi>judge our brethren about the uſe, or abſtinence from thoſe things which in their own nature are indifferent.</hi> In this caſe the Apoſtle puts the queſtion,<note place="margin">Sunt quaeiam facta media quae ignoramus quo an mo ſiam qaia &amp; bono, &amp; malo ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, de quibu. temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium eſt judicare maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ut condemnemus. <hi>Aug. de Serm, Dom. in Mont. l. 2. c. 18.</hi>
                  </note> Rom. 14.4. <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his own Maſter he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth or falleth.</hi> And for the <hi>abſtinence from ſuch things,</hi> the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let no man judge you;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calvin in loc.</note> and that is (as one explains it) <hi>make guilty of Judgement,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> (to wit) for the omiſſion of ſuch Ceremonies as were aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Our <hi>Suspicions muſt not ſerve us to condemn our brethren; for thoſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe <hi>ſecret things of the heart,</hi> it is Gods work to bring
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170181:35"/>them to light, 1 Cor. 4 3. <hi>Suspicions</hi> are no <hi>Proof,</hi> and therefore not a ſufficient foundation of a Legal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: No, nor every <hi>Report</hi> is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to raiſe a miſt, whereby to darken the reputation of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: for we know, <hi>SI SATIS F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERIT ACC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SASSE, NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MO ERIT INNOCENS, If it were ſufficient to accuſe, none ſhould be innocent.</hi> We muſt therefore in this caſe take Gods counſel, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his practice. Firſt, <hi>We muſt take his counſel,</hi> Deut. 13.14. They were not upon a bare report, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them who ſaid, <hi>Let us go and ſerve other gods.</hi> (But minde) thou ſhalt <hi>inquire, make ſearch,</hi> and <hi>ask diligently:</hi> and behold, if it be truth, and the thing certain, <hi>then</hi> do <hi>thus</hi> and <hi>thus.</hi> Again, ſee Gods <hi>Practice,</hi> Gen. 18.21. There God, who is Omniſcient, ſaw their ſin, the cry thereof came unto heaven, yet ſpeaking to our capacity, and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting our duty; <hi>I will go down now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſee whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170181:35"/>will know.</hi> This is the <hi>ſecond thing</hi> we muſt avoid then in judging: <hi>we muſt not condemn our brother</hi> for what we ſuppoſe or ſuſpect, before <hi>ſound ſearch</hi> after, and <hi>clear know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the fact.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and laſtly, <hi>We muſt not condemn our brother for ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular failing we clearly ſee in his life;</hi> either to the <hi>ſafety of his eſtate here,</hi> or the <hi>final ſecurity of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition hereafter.</hi> My meaning is this, If I ſee one, the more conſtant tenor of whoſe life hath been <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and the remembrance of his Name,</hi> through temptation hurried, or invigilancy intangled in any ſin, I muſt not cenſure this man to have been alwayes an <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> or condemn him as one who ſhall ever be a <hi>Reprobate:</hi> No, I am to look upon him as a diſlocated joynt in Chriſts Myſtical Body;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Gal. 6.1.</note> and therefore I muſt endevour to reſtore ſuch a one in the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> conſidering my ſelf, leſt <hi>I alſo be tempted.</hi> That mans tongue had <hi>out-run his wits,</hi> and charity alſo, who ſhould have (as it is to be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170181:36"/>thought many one did) counted <hi>David</hi> a Hypocrite before, or a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate after his two great ſins, <hi>Murther</hi> and <hi>Adulteny.</hi> But the Sun was never <hi>totally eclipſed,</hi> nor ſhall the <hi>candle</hi> of the righteous be put out <hi>in obſcurity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 37.24.</note> A righteous man may fall, but he ſhall not <hi>utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be caſt down:</hi> and it is the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Church, <hi>When I fall, I ſhall riſe; when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me,</hi> Mic. 17.8. Let me adde, Though the conſtant tenor of a mans life in ſin,<note place="margin">Duo autem ſunt in quibus temerarium ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium evitare debemus cumincertum eſt quo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo factum fuerit quic quid, &amp; quum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certum ſit: qualis fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus ſit, qui nunc vel honus, vel malus, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>Aug de Serm. Dom. l. 2. c. 18.</hi>
                  </note> may give us ground to think a man at the preſent, to be no better than <hi>a childe of wrath;</hi> yet this cannot warrant us to ſay, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after he ſhall be a <hi>ſon of perdition:</hi> for, <hi>INTER PONTEM ET FON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEM, MISERICOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIA DOMINI; God maketh our Neceſſity of help, his Opportunity to beſtow mercy.</hi> And he who here hath wallowed with Swine in the mire of ſin, may before he die be <hi>waſhed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170181:36"/>white in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> and made fit to lodge in <hi>Abraham his boſom.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimos ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarios, praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti amici la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titant, ad huc ignoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiam ſibi. <hi>Aug. de Civ. Dei, l: 1. c. 35.</hi>
                  </note> He who here had fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>with the unfruitful works of darkneſs,</hi> may through Gods renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace be <hi>made meet to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> hereafter, <hi>of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> We muſt not then, we cannot judge any, ſcarce as to their eſtate here, not at all to their weal or woe hereafter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> is that Jam. 2.12. <hi>So spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k ye, and ſo do, as they that ſhall be judged by the law of liberty.</hi> He founds his Exhortation upon the Rule of Judgement, <hi>The Law of Liberty:</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>Liberty, your Law;</hi> which Judge, many one would with their <hi>hearts and good will</hi> ſtand to: but that Law, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of which, makes you, ſpeaks you free, is certainly meant by the Apoſtle. Now he that will practiſe this duty, muſt obſerve theſe Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which will prepare him for the laſt and final Judgement by the <hi>Law of Liberty,</hi> the future <hi>Rule</hi> of our judgement.</p>
               <p>FIRST, that in Act 17.30. Let
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170181:37"/>our actions anſwer Gods injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is, that <hi>all men every where do repent.</hi> God gives a reaſon of this Command in the following verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath appointed a day, in the which he will judge the world in righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. This is the <hi>great Audit</hi> of Heaven, and God expects our <hi>Accounts</hi> ſhould be ready. It is <hi>Heavens Aſſizes,</hi> and God would give us notice to make ſure of our <hi>Advocate,</hi> leſt we be <hi>impleaded.</hi> It is the <hi>day of Hearing,</hi> and God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that our cauſe ſhould not then be to be <hi>commenced:</hi> and becauſe we cannot ſay we are innocent, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires we ſhould meet him with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> that ſo he may not <hi>lead us forth with the workers of iniquity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic agat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, ut illapoſſit mutaare ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam. <hi>Aug. de Sym. ad Cat. tract. 3. c. 8.</hi>
                  </note> He warns us to <hi>flee from the wrath to come,</hi> which cannot be, but by <hi>fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his mercy</hi> in Chriſt offered at the preſent: we ſhould meet him with ſorrow, that he may not cover our faces with ſhame; open our mouthes to him in confeſſion, leſt we ſtand ſpeechleſs before him at that great day. Let every one of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170181:37"/>us ſay, <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ID FECI? What have I done?</hi> leſt hereafter, in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Souls, each of us cry out, <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ID FACIAM? What ſhall I do, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us practice that,<note place="margin">Conſtitue te ante te; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcende tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis tuae, eſto ribi judex, torqueat te timor, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. in Pſal. 49.</hi>
                  </note>1 Cor. 11.31. <hi>Judge our ſelves, that we may not be judged.</hi> We ſhall not be condemned at the <hi>Great Aſſizes,</hi> if we judge our ſelves in our own <hi>Private Seſſions.</hi> If we would <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our wayes,</hi> God would not ſet our iniquities <hi>in order before us.</hi> When God doth open the Books, amongſt the which, that of his <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience</hi> will be one, all our debts will be found cancelled, wiped out with the blood of our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, if we waſh them with the tears of true Repentance. Aſſure we our ſelves, God will not <hi>ſeal up</hi> that mans <hi>iniquity in a bag,</hi> whoſe tears he putteth <hi>into his bottle.</hi> In that day the penitent ſinner ſhall <hi>lift up his head for joy,</hi> and know his <hi>Redeemer liveth;</hi> when the obſtinate ſinner ſhall not <hi>ſtand when he is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170181:38"/>judged.</hi> He who hath <hi>opened</hi> his mouth to God in <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> ſhall <hi>ſtop</hi> the Devils mouth, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting his <hi>Accuſation.</hi> Then ſhall that Promiſe have its full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.13</note> 
                  <hi>He that confeſſeth his ſins, ſhall finde mercy,</hi> when he that <hi>hideth them, ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Third thing,</hi> is that Act. 24.16. <hi>To Exerciſe our ſelves to have alwayes a Conſcience void of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence towards God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. de Fut. Jud. Hom. 25. Tom. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and toward men.</hi> This the Apoſtle tells us was the reſult of his Faith in the Reſurrection, which doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately precede the Judgement:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.9, 10.</note> to which alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſpecial regard, as an <hi>excellent Motive</hi> to a holy life. The ſame Conſcience which doth <hi>Abſolve us</hi> in this life, will alſo, under God, <hi>Acquit us</hi> in the other. A Conſcience which is here <hi>void of offence,</hi> will not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be filled with <hi>Complaints:</hi> but <hi>if our hearts condemn us, God is greater than our hearts, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170181:38"/>knoweth all things,</hi> 1 John 3.20. Repentance indeed is, <hi>TAB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LA POST NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>FRAGI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> But no man will ſink his Ship, truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a poſſibility of eſcaping drowning by a floating Plank: Nor ſhould we ſin, becauſe the <hi>Grace of God doth abound.</hi> No man runneth into Debt the more, becauſe he hopes for a Purſe to diſcharge it. Next to having our ſins <hi>blotted out</hi> of Gods Book, it is our greateſt happineſs, not at all to <hi>run upon the ſcore;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when God hath told us certainly, <hi>The Soul that ſinneth ſhall die;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> but hath left it at a <hi>peradventure,</hi> whether or no he will give us <hi>Repentance, to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Truth.</hi> He therefore that <hi>exerciſeth</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to keep his Conſcience <hi>void of offence,</hi> taketh the ſureſt courſe to be one, who <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.24.</note> though he may <hi>appear before Gods Tribunal;</hi> yet he ſhall not <hi>come into Condemnation.</hi> It is through Faith <hi>we are ſaved;</hi> but our Faith thus <hi>working by Love,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170181:39"/>herein is <hi>made perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.17</note> 
                  <hi>that we may have boldneſs in the Day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170181:39"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MAT. 25.46.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And theſe ſhall go away into Everlaſting Puniſhment; but the Righteous into Life Eternal.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Of HELL.</head>
               <p>I Have formerly ſpoken of <hi>Death,</hi> and its conſequent, <hi>Judgement:</hi> the which ſeeing it is terminated in a <hi>definitive Sentence</hi> of <hi>Abſolution</hi> or <hi>Condemnation,</hi> I have choſen theſe words, wherein we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the different eſtate of the <hi>Wicked</hi> and the <hi>Righteous</hi> after Judgement: <hi>They ſhall go away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170181:40"/>everlaſting puniſhment, but theſe into life eternal.</hi> And becauſe we judge of Contraries beſt,<note place="margin">Ideo autem hunc te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ordinem malui ut poſtea diſſeram de faeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate Sanctorum, nec à divinis ordo iſte abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret eloquiis &amp;c. <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei, lib. 21. cap. 1.</hi>
                  </note> where they are oppoſed each to the other (we know the <hi>pleaſure of light,</hi> by experiencing the <hi>terrors of darkneſs;</hi> the worth of <hi>health,</hi> by feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the woe which is in <hi>ſickneſs</hi>) I ſhall endevour to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your thoughts the nature or eſtate of <hi>Hell;</hi> that ſo we may with greater vehemency aſpire by our thoughts and actions towards <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſubject then of my preſent Diſcourſe, is, <hi>To Treat of Hell;</hi> in the <hi>Suburbs</hi> whereof, every Son of <hi>Adam</hi> is born, and therein doth <hi>inhabit;</hi> till being born again, he becometh <hi>the Son of God,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, <hi>an Heir</hi> of Eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. In theſe words, we have theſe parts.</p>
               <p>FIRST,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>The Perſons;</hi> which are <hi>two ſorts</hi> expreſſed under theſe terms: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is to ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Wicked,</hi> thoſe on the <hi>left hand:</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170181:40"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Righteous</hi> on the <hi>right hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their Places, which are as different as their Perſons. The one ſhall go, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the other, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: the former of which is <hi>Everlaſting;</hi> the latter, <hi>Eternal.</hi> I ſhall endevour to ſpeak to both in their order.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> The Propoſition I obſerve from the <hi>firſt</hi> part, is,
<q>That the Portion of the Wicked is everlaſting Puniſhment:</q>
               </p>
               <p>Or in the words of the Pſalmiſt:
<q>The Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell.<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.17.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe I need not multiply pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to evince the truth of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: if any man doubt of it, let him conſult his Conſcience; the <hi>ſecret rebukes</hi> whereof, do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times anticipate Hell, and give the ſinner an <hi>earnest</hi> of that <hi>Sum</hi> of Miſery, the payment whereof never ſhall have end. Let me
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170181:41"/>ask ſuch a ſinner, if he feel nòt that <hi>Worm</hi> crawling in his breſt, which ſhall <hi>never die?</hi> If he is not ſometimes even <hi>ſcorched</hi> in this life, with ſome <hi>sparks</hi> of that <hi>unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire?</hi> But I ſhould be ſorry to think my ſelf ſpeaking to any who are worſe than the Devils who <hi>believe</hi> what I am about to ſpeak, <hi>and</hi> do <hi>tremble.</hi> I therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to open this Abyſs of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to bring to light the ſtate of this place of Darkneſs, by conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in theſe reſpects:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Secundum Materiam, Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its Matter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Secundum Modum, Its Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Secundum Menſuram, Its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Secundum Durationem, Its Duration.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak to Hell, and the Torments thereof, according to all theſe reſpects.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Firſt:</hi> When I ſpeak of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170181:41"/>this <hi>Materia Gehennae,</hi> my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is not problematically to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, or poſitively to aſſert any <hi>Corporeal fire</hi> in that place of Torment,<note place="margin">Aquinas Suppl. ad <hi>3.</hi> partem, Queſt. <hi>97.</hi> Art. <hi>5.</hi> Bellarm. de Purgat. lib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> Eligat quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quod placet, aut ignem tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere corpori, animo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem hoc propriè, illud topice, &amp;c. <hi>Auguſt. de Civ. Dei, l. 21. c. 9.</hi> Qui ignis, cujuſmodi &amp; in qua mundi vel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum parte futurus ſit hominem ſcire arbitror neminem. <hi>Ibid. de Civit. Dei, l. 20. c. 16.</hi>
                  </note> which ſome out of choice, rather than with clearneſs have poſſibly underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: But my deſign is to treat of that <hi>Materîa circa quam,</hi> that object upon which theſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal flames are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; as alſo the <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ex qua,</hi> that <hi>Pabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ignis,</hi> the <hi>fewel</hi> and <hi>foment</hi> of thoſe everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burnings. And as to the firſt, we are to know, That <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body conjoyn'd,</hi> are the adequate objects of this eternal fury. They have been partakers in ſin, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall be ſharers in ſuffering; though the Soul, as it was the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal</hi> and <hi>Ring-leader</hi> of this Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt its Creator, ſhall have the firſt and deepeſt taſte of this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. Look as the Body, whilſt in this life, by reaſon of the corruption
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170181:42"/>of the Soul, was made an inſtrument thereof to act impiety: ſo when they are in Hell, the Soul ſhall be the <hi>Efficient</hi> of that vexation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh which ſhall ſeize upon the Body. Even as we ſee here they do ſympathize together, and partake of the weal or woe of either in this life: Though I deny not but God doth <hi>poſitively</hi> inflict his wrath on the Body, as well as on the Soul, as we ſhall hear further ere long.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let us ſee what is the <hi>Materia ex qua,</hi> that which doth <hi>kindle,</hi> and doth <hi>keep alive</hi> thoſe <hi>coals</hi> of fire, which are <hi>heaped</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heads of the wicked; and that is <hi>Sin.</hi> This is that which was the <hi>Parent of Helliſh ſorrow,</hi> which did dig that <hi>Bottomleſs Pit,</hi> and doth <hi>daily inlarge</hi> the Mouth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. We loſt our Right <hi>to Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> when we let go our Title to <hi>Holineſs;</hi> and ever ſince we have <hi>departed from God,</hi> our ſteps have <hi>took hold of Hell;</hi> which is the production of the <hi>Creature,</hi> not at all the operation of the Creator:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170181:42"/>and though he execute it as an act of his Juſtice,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Theoph. in Mat. 23.41.</note> yet he approveth not of it, when it <hi>comes in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition</hi> with his Mercy: for, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord, I deſire not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turn from his iniquity, and live,</hi> Ezek. 33.11. And thus much for the <hi>firſt</hi> Conſideration of Hell and its Torments.</p>
               <p>SECONDLY,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We are to conſider it, <hi>Secundum Modum, according to the Manner</hi> of that eſtate: And this will further deſcry the nature of theſe Torments; the manner of which, conſiſteth
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>In privation of Infinite Good.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>In poſition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is that <hi>Paena damni.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second,</hi> that <hi>Paena ſenſus</hi> which thoſe miſerable Creatures do lie under.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>Privation</hi> is part of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170181:43"/>the nature of Hell, ſeems to have ſome ground from this expreſſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>they ſhall go away;</hi> there is then <hi>terminus à quo, from which</hi> they depart, as well as <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ad quem, whither</hi> they go: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ab à privativo &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is an Etymologie which every <hi>School-boy</hi> is acquainted with: and ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the <hi>nature</hi> of Hell. There is a <hi>twofold</hi> privation which I ſhall touch upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>A Privation of all outward enjoyments,</hi> of whatſoever the world calls good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and <hi>chiefly,</hi> A privation of the <hi>Beatifical Viſion.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if the former were all,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Chryſ. ad Theod. lapſ. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raen.</note> Hell were ſomething <hi>tolerable;</hi> there being nothing <hi>without</hi> a man, in the abſence whereof he may not retain his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs But yet that is not inconſiderable in this <hi>forlorn eſtate,</hi> becauſe whilſt wicked men have their outward comforts about them, they do ſomewhat <hi>ſtupifie Conſcience,</hi> and put <hi>far from them the evil day.</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170181:43"/>But in <hi>Hell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Chryſoſt. ad Theod. lapſ. Paraen.</note> 
                  <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall finde no <hi>Cities</hi> to build; nor ſhall his Poſterity <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> to themſelves <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Muſick;</hi> none among them will take the <hi>Timbrel and Harp, or rejoyce at the ſound of the Organ. Belſhazzar</hi> cannot there drink <hi>wine in bowls,</hi> or eat the <hi>lambs out of the flock,</hi> or the <hi>Calves out of the midſt of the ſtall.</hi> The rich man ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his delicate diſhes, and that fine raiment wherewith he was <hi>clad every day.</hi> There are no <hi>Dice,</hi> whereby to <hi>caſt care away;</hi> nor <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> wherein to <hi>drown his grief. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> her <hi>Paint</hi> ſhall there be melted off, and <hi>burning ſhall be in ſtead of beauty.</hi> Neither ſhall <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>Bag</hi> afford him a <hi>crum</hi> of Comfort: for, <hi>in one hour, ſo great delights are come to nought.</hi> But this is the <hi>leaſt part</hi> of their loſs; for theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhall be deprived of him, in whoſe Preſence is <hi>fulneſs of joy,</hi> and at whoſe <hi>right hand are pleaſures for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170181:44"/>evermore. Depart from me,</hi> ver. 41. is the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>worſt</hi> of that <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Sentence which ſuch ſhall hear. How ſhall <hi>Amazement</hi> and <hi>Horror,</hi> the pangs as <hi>of a woman in travail,</hi> ſeize upon the Souls of theſe accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Caitiffs, when the <hi>Lamb of God</hi> ſhall utter his voice like <hi>a Lion,</hi> in that terrible Sentence, <hi>Depart from me;</hi> each <hi>ſyllable</hi> whereof doth <hi>pronounce</hi> amazement, <hi>accent grief,</hi> and will cauſe their Souls to <hi>meditate Terror,</hi> whom it doth concern. Thus thoſe who did <hi>forget the God that formed them,</hi> ſhall be <hi>cut off from his hand, and be remembred no more.</hi> They who were the <hi>Servants of Sin,</hi> ſhall be <hi>free amongst the dead.</hi> They who were <hi>wiſe to do evil,</hi> whilſt they ſuffer the <hi>terrors</hi> of the Lord, ſhall <hi>be diſtracted.</hi> They who <hi>wearied</hi> themſelves to <hi>commit iniquity,</hi> ſhall finde, that the <hi>wages of ſin is death,</hi> when they ſhall <hi>reap the fruit of their own doings,</hi> and their back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings ſhall <hi>correct them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I proceed to the Second (to wit) <hi>Poſition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nspeakable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And here were my Tongue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170181:44"/>as the <hi>Pen of a ready wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. ad Theod. lapſ. Paraen. Pſal. 108.11.</note> I ſhould fail in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Torments which <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive.</hi> If we reſpect the Soul, <hi>great</hi> is the miſery inflicted on it. Let us then judge of the <hi>Lion by his Paw,</hi> and that <hi>Ocean</hi> of wrath, by thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. ad Theod lapſ. Paraen.</note> 
                  <hi>Drops</hi> thereof, which fall ſometimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men on this ſide the Infernal Pit. If theſe do <hi>drown</hi> men in ſorrow and ſadneſs, what will be the caſe of ſuch, when God ſhall afflict them with <hi>all his waves?</hi> when the terrors of the Lord ſhall <hi>come round about</hi> a Soul,<note place="margin">Pſa. 88.17.</note> and <hi>compaſs</hi> it about together? when the Lord ſhall meet ſuch a Soul, as <hi>a Bear which is robbed of her whelps,</hi> and ſhall <hi>rend the caul of his heart?</hi> when he ſhall make the wicked as a <hi>fiery oven in the time of his anger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 29.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall ſwallow them up in his wrath, and the fire ſhall devour them?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 7.15.</note> when God <hi>ſhall hunt them
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170181:45"/>as a fierce Lion,</hi> and the Almighty ſhall ſet himſelf againſt a ſinner in <hi>battel aray?</hi> How would ſuch a Soul chooſe <hi>ſtrangling and death, rather than life?</hi> But this is not all, though <hi>the chiefeſt</hi> of their ſorrow; for the Body <hi>hath ſinned,</hi> and muſt alſo ſuffer: That fleſh which <hi>hath ſwimmed</hi> in pleaſures, ſhall be <hi>drench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in rivers of Brimſtone:</hi> Thoſe eyes, which were ſometimes the <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of vanity,</hi> ſhall now be the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of ghaſtly ſpectacles:</hi> Thoſe ears, which were <hi>delighted</hi> formerly with <hi>corrupt communication,</hi> ſhall now be <hi>affrighted</hi> with <hi>hideous yellings</hi> of thoſe damned creatures: The <hi>curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſmell,</hi> ſtopped <hi>with the ſtench</hi> of that infernal place: That <hi>nice palate,</hi> ſhall want its <hi>curious</hi> fare; when he who was <hi>mighty to drink wine,</hi> and a man of <hi>ſtrength to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſtrong drink,</hi> ſhall <hi>feed upon wormwood,</hi> and <hi>drink the water of gall:</hi> The <hi>delicate touch</hi> ſhall no longer then be pleaſed, when he who was accuſtomed to <hi>ſtretch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon Beds of Ivory,</hi> ſhall have this at <hi>the hand of the Lord,</hi> to <hi>lie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170181:45"/>down in ſorrow.</hi> This will ſilence each <hi>curſing Shimei,</hi> who <hi>addeth grief to the ſorrow</hi> of Gods people, by <hi>reproachful taunts;</hi> and tie the tongues of thoſe <hi>railing Rabſhekahs,</hi> who love <hi>all devouring words:</hi> For the tongue of the Slanderer ſhall not then be at liberty to <hi>walk up and down the earth,</hi> when its <hi>impriſonment in Hell</hi> ſhall controll it: The hands of the <hi>violent perſon</hi> ſhall be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacled</hi> there, and <hi>ceaſe</hi> to oppreſs; and the feet of him who was <hi>ſwift to ſhed blood,</hi> ſhall be <hi>reſerved in everlaſting chains of darkneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 18.17</note> And by how much the more ſuch have <hi>glorified</hi> themſelves, and lived <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly,</hi> ſo much <hi>torment</hi> ſhall be <hi>given</hi> unto them. Were their ſtrength the <hi>ſtrength of ſtones,</hi> or their fleſh <hi>of braſs,</hi> yet how could they <hi>harden themſelves in this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row?</hi> Can their hearts <hi>endure,</hi> or can their hands <hi>be ſtrong in the day that the Lord ſhall deal with them?</hi> it's Gods own queſtion, Ezek. 22 14. Yet <hi>endure they muſt,</hi> and that <hi>more</hi> than I have yet named. And this leads me to the <hi>Third</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170181:46"/>of theſe Torments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secundum Menſuram,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Meaſure or Degree of them:</hi> and this is <hi>exceeding</hi> great, yet <hi>various,</hi> according to the ſeveral demerits of the ſinner; for ſuch as <hi>rebel againſt the light,</hi> is reſerved <hi>the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever: LAESA PATIENTIA FIT F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROR, Love ſlighted, turns to irreconcileable hatred.</hi> The <hi>Gulf</hi> between Heaven and Hell is made more <hi>wide,</hi> by neglecting <hi>great Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> It ſhall be <hi>more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon in the day of Judgement, than for Chorazin and Bethſaida,</hi> wherein Chriſt did his <hi>mighty works.</hi> We poor Mortals (until God do bring us from under the <hi>power of Satan</hi> to himſelf) do live in the world, as if Hell were not ſo <hi>hot,</hi> or the Devil ſo <hi>black,</hi> as indeed he is; as if Hell and Heaven were <hi>Nuga tricae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> the one not worth the avoiding, the other not worth the enjoying: But the <hi>heat</hi> of fire was never <hi>painted;</hi> and the Devil is more deformed, than repreſented on the wall; there
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170181:46"/>are <hi>unexpreſſible</hi> Torments in Hell, as well as <hi>unspeakable</hi> Joyes in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Some who write of <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellarm. de Purg. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> Bellarm. de Aeter. Faeli. Sanct. l. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Boſquier Dom. in feſto poſt pentec. tom. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> tell us, the pains thereof are more exquiſite, <hi>(though of ſhort continuance)</hi> than the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Torments that the earth can invent, though of longer duration. If the <hi>Popes Kitchin</hi> be ſo warm, how hot is the <hi>Devils Furnace?</hi> A Poetical Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is but a <hi>Mei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <l>Paena autem vehemens ac multo ſevior illis,</l>
                     <l>Quas &amp; Ceditius gravis inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit aut Radamanthus</l>
                     <l>Nocte diéque ſuum geſtare in pectore teſten.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Juv. Sat. 13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </note> when brought to ſhew the nature of theſe real Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The laſhes of Furies are but petty ſcourgings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when compared to the ſtripes of a wounded Conſcience: <hi>Tytius</hi> his Vulture, though feeding on his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is but a Flea-biting to that Worm which gnaweth their Hearts, and dieth not: <hi>Ixion</hi> his Wheel is a place of reſt, if compared with thoſe Billows of Wrath, and that Wheel of Juſtice, which is in Hell brought over the ungodly: The task of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naus</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170181:47"/>his Daughters is but a ſport, compared to the torture of thoſe, whoſe Souls are <hi>filled with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> within whom are the <hi>Arrows</hi> of the Almighty, the <hi>poiſon</hi> whereof doth <hi>drink up their ſpirit.</hi> Look as men did <hi>drink iniquity like water,</hi> ſo God will <hi>pour out the vials of his wrath;</hi> they preſſed him under their ſins, he will <hi>load</hi> them with his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and indignation;<note place="margin">Deut. 32.22.</note> they <hi>heaped up</hi> their ſins as high as Heaven, the fire which is kindled in his anger, ſhall <hi>burn unto the loweſt Hell;</hi> their ſins have been <hi>increaſed,</hi> his wrath is <hi>treaſured up,</hi> the meaſure whereof appears from the ſeveral Names it is intitled with.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.42. Luk. 16.28.</note> It is called, <hi>A furnace of fire,</hi> which ſpeaketh <hi>intolerable heat;</hi> A <hi>place of Torment,</hi> which ſpeaketh a <hi>total privation of eaſe;</hi> A <hi>Priſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.25. &amp; 5.22.</note> which ſpeaketh <hi>reſtraint; Gehenna,</hi> from the Valley of <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom,</hi> where the unnatural Parents did ſacrifice <hi>the fruit of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> for the <hi>ſin of their Souls,</hi> to their mercileſs Idols. The which word,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gehenne</hi> vox Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> by a <hi>Neighbour Nation,</hi> is retained, to ſignifie <hi>a Rack;</hi> than
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170181:47"/>the Torture of which,<note place="margin">Rev. 20.10</note> what more exquiſite? It is called <hi>A Lake of fire and Brimſtone;</hi> than the <hi>torment</hi> of the former, what more acute? than the <hi>ſmell</hi> of the latter, what more noiſom? There is heat, yet <hi>no light;</hi> for it is termed<note place="margin">Mat. 25.30.</note> 
                  <hi>outer darkneſs.</hi> In a word, he hath made it <hi>deep and large,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Hom. 25. de fut. jud. tom. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the pile thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a ſtream of brimſtone doth kindle it,</hi> Iſa. 30.33. But yet if I have not ſufficiently ſet out the meaſure thereof, if we believe not <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> which are with us, let us <hi>impannel a Jury</hi> from <hi>Hell,</hi> let them <hi>from the dead</hi> ſpeak, and ſee if their Verdict amount not to this. <hi>It is an evil and bitter thing to depart from God, and that his fear was not in them.</hi> What ſaiſt thou, O <hi>Cain,</hi> is the <hi>fire of Hell</hi> more delightful than the <hi>flames of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love</hi> thou didſt abhor to live in, whilſt in the world? Thou alſo, O <hi>Achitophel,</hi> is thy <hi>Treaſon</hi> and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170181:48"/>
                  <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nihil proderit damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quod in hac vitâ in perpetuâ ſaturitate, &amp; ebrietate vixerunt, quia tunc ne guttu am qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem aquae obtiuere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt. Nihil proderit eis quod veſtibus uſi fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint splendidis, quia induentur confuſione &amp; corpora ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum veſtien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>iâ. Nihil proderit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quod in hac vitâ conſtituti fuerint in honoribus, quia in inferno nullus erit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> inuus gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; dolor. <hi>Ger. Med. 49.</hi>
                  </note> rewarded with that repute thou didſt expect? What thinkeſt thou, O <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar,</hi> is the Cup of the <hi>red wine of the fury of the Lord,</hi> as pleaſing to thy taſte, as thy wine drunk in thy <hi>ſacrilegious bowls?</hi> Tell us, O <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> will <hi>thirty pieces</hi> out-value the loſs of an immortal Soul, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the miſery of <hi>ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred and odde</hi> years in that <hi>place of darkneſs?</hi> Or reſolve us, O <hi>Herod,</hi> whether the breath of the Lord, which keepeth alive theſe <hi>eternal Coals,</hi> doth <hi>tickle</hi> thy fancy, as ſometimes <hi>vulgar air,</hi> or <hi>popular breath,</hi> now thou art proved a Man, and no <hi>God,</hi> by being brought down to the ſides of the Pit? The <hi>Fore-man</hi> ſpeaks in theſe and the reſt of their Names, <hi>My puniſhment is greater than I can bear?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I now proceed to conſider it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170181:48"/>
                  <hi>Secundum Durationem, In its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance:</hi> and we need not go far for the reſolution of this; for it is called in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. ad Theod. lapſ. Parae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puniſhment,</hi> the end thereof is not known, its duration is undetermin'd. Hell is a <hi>bott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mleſs pit,</hi> and therefore ſhall <hi>never</hi> be fathomed: It is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>an unquenchable fire;</hi> and therefore the <hi>ſmoke of their torments doth aſcend for ever and ever,</hi> Rev 4.12. Hell is <hi>a Priſon,</hi> from whence is no <hi>freedom;</hi> becauſe no Ranſom to be paid, no price will be accepted for one in that eſtate. When we lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>great</hi> ſorrows, <hi>ſinking troubles,</hi> yet this ſtrengthens us, <hi>Dabit Deus his quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> finem, God will put an end to all theſe.</hi> But this is that which will augment the miſery of a damned creature, he is ſenſible his caſe is ſad, he is <hi>ſure</hi> God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed it ſhall be no better: the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful reflection upon which, ſhall <hi>wound his Soul,</hi> and in the anguiſh thereof cauſe him to utter with his
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170181:49"/>mouth, what his heart is aſtoniſhed at, <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi> This is the portion of thoſe, whoſe Souls are removed <hi>far off from peace,</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get prosperity;</hi> in the bitterneſs whereof they complain, <hi>My ſtrength and my hope is periſh'd from the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt I have been thus reaſoning of Judgement to come, poſſibly ſome <hi>Felix</hi> may tremble, the thoughts of Hell may have kindled ſome affection towards heaven, and he whom the love of <hi>Chriſt</hi> could not <hi>conſtrain,</hi> yet the <hi>terror of the Lord</hi> may have <hi>almoſt perſwaded</hi> to be a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cyr. Chat. 15. p. 389.</note> being fore-warned, he may deſire to <hi>flee from this wrath to come.</hi> Such I ſhall ſend to <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> for direction in this caſe, Mat. 3.8. <hi>Bring forth fruits worthy of amendment of life:</hi> Avoid thoſe ſins which do in a <hi>principal manner</hi> lead to theſe <hi>chambers of death,</hi> and bring forth the <hi>fruits of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the <hi>end</hi> whereof is <hi>Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170181:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. What are thoſe ſins which God hath affixed his condemnatory Sentence to the Commiſſion of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer indefinitely in the language of the Apoſtle, <hi>The wages of ſin;</hi> that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Rom. 6 23.</note> of <hi>every</hi> ſin is <hi>death:</hi> but more particularly God hath <hi>revealed his wrath from heaven</hi> againſt thoſe ſins, which he doth u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually reſerve to puniſh in Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This is that ſin which firſt made the breach between God and Man, and hath ever ſince continued the fewd: This was that, which laid the foundation of Hell, that digged that Pit of Perdition: This is that which vilifieth God, <hi>it maketh him a liar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.10</note> it <hi>eclipſeth the Sun of Righteouſneſs;</hi> no wonder then if God will puniſh it in <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting darkneſs:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chry. hom 25. de fut. jud. tom. 6.</note> not believing of Hell, doth make more <hi>broad</hi> the way which leadeth to deſtruction. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief in the heart,</hi> is always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>ignorance in the head;</hi> and againſt both, Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is directed; 2 Theſſ. 1.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Detraction. Whiſperers</hi> and <hi>Back-biters,</hi> are joyned in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170181:50"/>Catalogue with <hi>haters of God,</hi> who are <hi>worthy of death,</hi> Rom. 1.31. The Detractor,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Tim. 3.11.</note> is a <hi>Devil above ground,</hi> his tongue is already <hi>ſet on fire</hi> from Hell, which doth ſadly preſage what will be the portion of the Soul and Body for ever, unleſs Repentance <hi>quench</hi> thoſe flames. He who hath here <hi>ſwords in his lips,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 59.11.</note> may expect hereafter his iniquity ſhould be <hi>upon his bones:</hi> He that <hi>ſmiteth</hi> others with his tongue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may expect the <hi>Arrows</hi> of Gods Quiver to <hi>enter into his reins.</hi> In a word, he in whoſe mouth is a <hi>rod of pride,</hi> may fear to be broke in pieces as a <hi>potters veſſel,</hi> by the <hi>ſtaff of Gods indignation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> God will make a <hi>right</hi> path for his Juſtice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe, who <hi>turn aſide</hi> from him by their <hi>crooked wayes.</hi> The Holy Tongue admits not of the <hi>Neuter Gender,</hi> nor will the God of Holineſs allow <hi>neutrality in any perſon:</hi> for, <hi>The hypocrite in heart heapeth up wrath,</hi> Job 36.13. and we finde <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> meet together in that place of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170181:50"/>and their Griefs made the <hi>Standards</hi> of others ſufferings Mat. 24.51. Luk 12.41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> This ſhall abide the trial of theſe <hi>(I ſay not)</hi> cleanſing flames. They who have <hi>burned in the fire of lust,</hi> muſt not think much to be <hi>ſcorched in the flames of Hell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 7.12.</note> He who went after that Harlot (as <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribes him) <hi>as an Ox</hi> goeth <hi>to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſhall finde in this place what follows, He ſhall go <hi>as a fool to the correction of the ſtocks.</hi> She to whom <hi>ſtoln waters were ſweet,</hi> and <hi>bread eaten in ſecret was pleaſant,</hi> ſhall <hi>vomit up</hi> thoſe <hi>ſweet morſels,</hi> and her mouth ſhall be <hi>filled with gravel.</hi> She who perfumed her bed with <hi>Myrrhe, Aloes and Cinnamon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 7.17, 18.</note> ſhall finde the <hi>end</hi> thereof as <hi>bitter as wormwood, as ſharp as a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged ſword:</hi> whilſt they who go aſtray in <hi>her paths,</hi> ſhall finde that <hi>her</hi> houſe is the <hi>way to Hell,</hi> Prov. 7.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly, SENS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALITY.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>A loving of pleaſures more than loving of God: The Harp, and the Viol,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſ. 5.12, 14</note>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170181:51"/>
                  <hi>the Tabret, and the Pipe, and wine are in their feaſts; but they regard not the work of the Lord, neither conſider the operation of his hands: therefore Hell hath inlarged it ſelf, and opened her mouth without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that they who</hi> did thus <hi>ſpend their dayes in mirth,</hi> may in a <hi>moment</hi> deſcend thereinto. Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to <hi>none ſo ſudden;</hi> as to the ſenſual perſon.<note place="margin">Dan. 5.5.</note> Whilſt <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> is taſting his wine, in the <hi>ſame hour</hi> come forth the <hi>fingers of a mans hands,</hi> and write his doom. When the rich man cries,<note place="margin">Lu. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe;</hi> God <hi>breaks</hi> his ſleep with that terrible voice, <hi>Thou fool; this night ſhall they require thy Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I ſpoken to this <hi>eſtate</hi> or <hi>place</hi> of Hell. I ſhould next diſcourſe of Heaven, and there <hi>Senſe</hi> will be the beſt Orator. He alone can deſcribe it, who liveth in the <hi>fruition</hi> thereof. But yet the People of God are not left in the dark, concerning the nature of this <hi>Inheritance</hi> of the Saints <hi>in light.</hi> They behold through a Glaſs yet <hi>darkly,</hi> that which ere
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170181:51"/>long they ſhall ſee <hi>face to face:</hi> Even in this Wilderneſs of the world they have a <hi>Piſgah-ſight</hi> of the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> the deſcription whereof followeth in the next Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170181:52"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>MAT. 25.46.</bibl>
                     <p>But the Righteous into Life Eternal.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Of HEAVEN.</head>
               <p>IN the former part of this Verſe, you had the <hi>black</hi> ſide of the Cloud, here you have the <hi>bright</hi> part thereof; you ſaw the mouth of the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit</hi> opened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the <hi>Heavens</hi> opened, and the righteous aſcending thereinto. I have ſpoken of Hell, let me now endevour to ſhew you the eſtate of the Saints in Heaven: But <hi>how ſhall we ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange land?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 137.4.</note> was ſometimes the ſorrowful
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170181:52"/>
                  <hi>quaere</hi> of the Jews So I ſay,<note place="margin">Quis audet de his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, poſitus in hac mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tali carne, quae aggravat animam aliquid dicere? cum Paulus Apoſtolus hoc non valuit explicare, qui in iſto poſitus corpore uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in tertium caelum gratiâ operante valuit aſcendere. <hi>Auguſt. de Sym. ad Cat. lib. 2. cap. 12.</hi>
                  </note> Think not that I can deſcribe theſe <hi>Manſions of Glory,</hi> who am <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned</hi> in a <hi>houſe of Clay;</hi> the which whilſt I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, my eyes are <hi>dazled,</hi> my hand doth <hi>waver,</hi> whilſt I undertake to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them; and I can but <hi>liſp</hi> forth my <hi>half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceptions</hi> of the feliciry of that ſtate:<note place="margin">Non poſſum dicere, quia nec videre poſſum, tamen aliquid non im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudenter dico, qui ex Scaipturis dico. <hi>Aug. Ser. 10 de Reſur. mort.</hi>
                  </note> yet ſo far as Scripture will give leave, I ſhall endevour the proſecution of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: for it muſt be an <hi>Angel</hi> from heaven, or ſome bleſſed <hi>Saint,</hi> who with that holy Apoſtle hath been eaught up into the <hi>third Heaven,</hi> who can conceive theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which concern that eſtate. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which, I ſhall expreſs my thoughts of it, by proſecuting this Doctrine: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <q>That the reward of the Righteous is Eternal Life.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170181:53"/>
               <p>In ſpeaking to which, I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this <hi>Recompence of Reward,</hi> this <hi>gift of God, Eternal Life,</hi> much after my method uſed in ſpeaking to the <hi>wages of ſin,</hi> Hell, or Death, and ſo we may view it,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Quoad Subjectum, According to the Subject.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Quoad Modum, The Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Quoad Menſuram, The Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Quoad Durationem, The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum in quo, The Subject in which</hi> this <hi>Glory</hi> ſhall be revealed, this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life</hi> ſhall reſide: and what God will conjoyn in this eſtate of Bliſs, let not me ſeparate. The Subject then of this Happineſs, is <hi>the Body and Soul re-united:</hi> The Body, as well as the Soul, was an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> of grace here; it ſhall be a <hi>veſſel</hi> of glory hereafter: both of them had their <hi>fruit unto holineſs,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of both ſhall be <hi>Eternal
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170181:53"/>Life.</hi> The Body without the Soul is <hi>incapable of;</hi> the Soul without the Body is <hi>incomplete</hi> in this Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happineſs. They were <hi>Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litones in pugna,</hi> they ſhall be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortes in praemio:</hi> It is ſtyled,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. 8.18</hi> Putas qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis tunc erit ſplendor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimarum quando ſolis claritatem habebit lux corporum. <hi>Aug. Ser. 12. in verb. Apoſt: 2 Cor. 5.10 1 Cor. 15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Glory revealed in us.</hi> Not to ſpeak then of the Soul, which is the <hi>proximate</hi> Subject thereof, and therefore ſhall excel that of the body: Let us a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſee what Scripture ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that whereof the <hi>Body</hi> ſhall be a partaker. <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to us the eſtate of the Body in the Reſurrection thereof, doth in ſome meaſure repreſent to us the eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te it ſhall for ever continue in. The Body of a man, conſidered in this preſent condition it is in, is of little worth, had it nota reference to an Eternity, which is future. It is <hi>corruptible, diſhonourable, infirm, natural;</hi> but when it is raiſed again, this <hi>corruptible,</hi> doth <hi>put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> that which was <hi>ſown in diſhonour,</hi> is <hi>raiſed in glory;</hi> that which was <hi>ſown in weakneſs,</hi> is <hi>rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedin power.</hi> In a word, that which was ſown <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a natural
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170181:54"/>body</hi> ſhall be raiſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a spiritual body.</hi> So far then as theſe oppoſites excel each the other, ſo far ſhall the eſtate of the Body which is <hi>future,</hi> excel that which is at preſent. But the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth yet more <hi>lively</hi> delineate the future glory of the body. So great ſhall the change thereof be,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> that it ſhall be <hi>faſhioned like unto the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is here <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a vile body;</hi> or which is worſe, <hi>a body of vileneſs. Ante ortum ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma faetidum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gerhar. Med. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>in vita ſaccus ſtercorum poſt mortem cibus vermium.</hi> This is the condition of all: But <hi>Gods people</hi> are exceeding vile in the eyes of others, and are yet more vile in their own eyes. Oh but in that day, when God doth make up <hi>his jewels,</hi> he will remember them, when he will caſt aſide many a <hi>glittering ſtone.</hi> He will be glorified in them who were <hi>deſpiſed</hi> becauſe of him; he will deſpiſe thoſe, in whoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he was not precious: the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall <hi>awake to ſhame, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting contempt,</hi> but the former ſhall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170181:54"/>
                  <hi>ſhine as the brightneſs of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>as the ſtars for ever and ever.</hi> And this for the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let us conſider it <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OAD MOD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M, according to the Manner of this Eternal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:</hi> And ſo we ſhall finde it conſiſts,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>In Remotione Malorum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>In Exhibitone Bonorum.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Removing</hi> what ſpeaketh <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery;</hi> in <hi>Conferring</hi> whatſoever is called <hi>Good.</hi> I begin with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, becauſe it is ever <hi>ſuppoſed,</hi> at leaſt effected by the latter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> then,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the <hi>Removal of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> doth ever accompany this eſtate of Happineſs. Now there are <hi>three</hi> great Miſeries under which holy men groan in this life, which they ſhall then be freed from:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Sin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Temptations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Sorrow.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>From all theſe, the Saints ſhall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170181:55"/>then be releaſed. I will ſpeak ſomewhat to them in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, Sin.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This is the <hi>ſource</hi> of all our miſery; and when we are freed from it, we ſhall be complete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy. This is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sin that dwelleth in us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.17</note> as the Apoſtle calls it. And therefore before we lay down this tabernable of our body,<note place="margin">Quia peccavit iſta natura, quum peccare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit, larg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore gratia li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratur, ut ad cam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducatur libertatem: in qua peccare non poſſit, ſic enim erit inamiſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis voluntas pietatis &amp; aequitatis, quomodo eſt faelicitatis. <hi>Auguſt. de Civ. Dci, l. 21. c. 30.</hi>
                  </note> it will not change its dwelling. An imperious Tenant, which will turn the <hi>Land-lord</hi> out of doors: But this is our comfort, it is a Tenant <hi>at will;</hi> I mean, at Gods will, who by our death ſhall deſtroy it. This, becauſe the neareſt, is therefore the greateſt grief to a godly heart. The ſin of others alſo is matter of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a pious Soul. But in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of life, righteous <hi>Lot</hi> ſhall no more be vexed in his Soul,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.7, 8.</note> with the the ungodly deeds of the unclean <hi>Sodomites:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 110.5.</note> Holy <hi>David</hi> ſhall not ſojourn in <hi>Meſhech,</hi> nor dwell in the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170181:55"/>tents of <hi>Kedar:</hi> Or <hi>Jeremiah</hi> wiſh for a <hi>lodging-place</hi> of <hi>wayfaring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the wilderneſs,</hi> that he might leave his people, and go from them. The choiceſt earthly contents are but a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or as a <hi>dream of the night,</hi> to thoſe heavenly delights, where each faculty of the Soul ſhall be ſetled in its <hi>primitive</hi> perfection, and each member of the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubſervient to the end of its Creation, The Glory of God, and the Comfort of the whole: The <hi>Law of the Members</hi> ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſht by the victorious ſtrength of the <hi>law of the Spirit of Life which is in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> Thoſe civil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in the minde of man ſhall ceaſe, and the bleſſed conquerors ſhal bear their <hi>Palms</hi> in their hands, and caſt their Crowns at the feet of him,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.15.</note> with whom they ſhall alſo <hi>reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, Temptations.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Theſe are part of the miſery of a holy man.<note place="margin">Nemo ſeeurus eſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet in hac vita, quae totae tentatio nominatur. <hi>Aug. Confeſ. lib. 10. cap. 32.</hi>
                  </note> Whilſt we are in this probation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, we cannot but be under a neceſſity of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with trials, whilſt on
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170181:56"/>this ſide heaven we are in danger of falling by them.<note place="margin">Vide Aug. de civ. Dci, l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Strait is the gate which leadeth unto heaven,</hi> and <hi>great,</hi> yea <hi>many</hi> are the ſtumbling-blocks to hinder our entrance. <hi>Narrow is the way which leadeth unto life,</hi> and many are the ſnares which are laid to hinder our progreſs thither. We open not our eyes, but we are ready to <hi>behold vanity;</hi> we hear not, but the Devil is ready by <hi>corrupt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> to <hi>corrupt</hi> our manners; we taſte not, but our <hi>wine is a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and our bread deceitful.</hi> The Devil hath <hi>bribed</hi> our ſenſes, and they are become purveyors of the fleſh: Even where we think our ſelves moſt ſafe, the Devil doth oft <hi>take us napping,</hi> even in our harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Recreations: <hi>Latet anguis in herba,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ipſum mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum per o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnes hor as tentationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus plenum. <hi>Auguſt. de civ. Dei, l. 1. c. 27.</hi>
                  </note> and we are ſtung ere we are aware. So that how true is that, <hi>In many things we offend all,</hi> Jam. 3.2. * Adde to all, <hi>Temptations</hi> from the <hi>World,</hi> ſuch whom the Pſalmiſt calls his<note n="†" place="margin">Vid. Byth. Prax. in Pſal. <hi>5.9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Obſervers,</hi> ſuch who <hi>watch</hi> for their <hi>haltings,</hi> and ſay as thoſe of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 20 10. <hi>Peradventure he will be enticed, and we ſhall prevail
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170181:56"/>againſt him, and we ſhall take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge on him.</hi> And if ſuch a mans foot <hi>ſlip,</hi> they <hi>magnifie</hi> themſelves againſt him. This is a <hi>ſword in the bones</hi> of Gods people,<note place="margin">Pſ. 42.10</note> (that I may uſe the Pſalmiſts expreſſion) a <hi>ſore</hi> and <hi>grievous</hi> temptation: But hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall free them from theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations. A Dog may <hi>bark</hi> at the Moon, but he cannot pull it from its Orb; and the Devil may <hi>howl</hi> at the Saints in bliſs through <hi>envy,</hi> but this <hi>great Dragon,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> is caſt out into the earth, and his <hi>Angels</hi> with him, and ſhall never come nearer to moleſt them.<note place="margin">Rev. 12.9.</note> And this is one Stave in the <hi>Song of the Lamb, Now is come Salvation, and Strength, and the Kingdom of God, and the Power of his Chriſt, for the Accuſer of our brethren is caſt down,</hi> Rev. 12.10. And they who watched the ſtumbling of Gods people, will have enough to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go their own miſery, now they themſelves are fallen into the Pit. Yea, theſe Sons of <hi>Zion,</hi> who by reaſon of adherent frailty, are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments ſometimes to each other
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170181:57"/>in the way,<note place="margin">Vita totius elegantiae &amp; dignitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pleniſſima ubi non eſt adver ſarius impugnans, ubi nulla peccati illecebris, ubi est amor perfectus &amp; timor nullus, ubi Deus aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; unus omnium ſpiritus. <hi>Aug. c. 22.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate their mutual arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val in their end; where thoſe <hi>flames</hi> of love ſhall put out the <hi>fire</hi> of all contention; thoſe <hi>rivers of pleaſure</hi> ſhall aſſwage the heat of thoſe <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xyſms</hi> of wrath,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Acts 15.39. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. ad Pheod. lapſ. Paraen:</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Gods people are too oft diſtempered in this humane ſtate. But there ſhall they be of <hi>one heart,</hi> and of <hi>one ſoul,</hi> one with God, at unity amongſt themſelves for evermore. Each <hi>Name of Diviſion</hi> will ceaſe, every <hi>Bone of Contention</hi> ſhall be caſt into the fire, each <hi>Rock of Offence</hi> taken away: Love, which was here <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choative,</hi> and in the <hi>increaſe,</hi> ſhall be there <hi>conſummate,</hi> and bleſſed <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> betwixt God and the Saints, ſhall render more happy their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> one with the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, Sorrow.</hi> This is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſery incumbent upon Gods people here. Every Son of the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> is born <hi>crying;</hi> and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170181:57"/>few of the children of the <hi>ſecond Adam</hi> live without <hi>tears</hi> upon their cheeks.<note place="margin">Infantia non à riſu ſed à fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u orditurh-n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lucem quo quid malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ingreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſit nejci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g. de civ. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> l. 21. c. 14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Every ſon whom he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, he chaſtiſeth,</hi> Heb. 12.6. He himſelf was a <hi>man of ſorrows:</hi> it cannot be expected then, that his ſhould be <hi>unacquainted with grief. David,</hi> a man of no melancholy temper yet complains, that his <hi>tears</hi> were his <hi>meat day and night,</hi> Pſa. 42.3. and elſwhere we hear him <hi>rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for the <hi>diſquietneſs</hi> of his Spirit. And the Prophet tells us of the Church in general,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>She weepeth ſore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks;</hi> and though <hi>ſhe spread forth her hands,</hi> yet there is <hi>none to comfort her.</hi> But what? <hi>Hath the Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to be gracious, and will he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his people no more?</hi> Yes ſurely, the time is approaching, when every <hi>Priſoner of Hope</hi> ſhall be ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,<note place="margin">Zech. 9.12</note> when ſorrow and ſighing ſhall <hi>flee away:</hi> when God ſhall <hi>wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorrow, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain.</hi> The Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden</hi> is but a Wilderneſs, if
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170181:58"/>compared to this <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of the Saints; wherein is <hi>that river,</hi> the ſtreams whereof thus <hi>make glad the City of God.</hi> Whence they, who whilſt on the earth did draw water out of the <hi>wells of Salvation,</hi> are as from a Fountain <hi>ſatis fied with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> and <hi>full of the bleſſing of the Lord:</hi> Their <hi>temporary</hi> flaſhes of peace, being kindled into flames of <hi>immortal</hi> joy. This is the ſtate of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> which is above: there is no ſuch humour as <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly</hi> in Heaven;<note place="margin">Vera ibi pax eſt ubi nihil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi nec à ſeipſo nec ab alio quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam patle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Aug. de civ. Dei l. 22.</hi> cr <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> thoſe: <hi>Helliſh fumes,</hi> that <hi>ſmoke</hi> from the <hi>Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit,</hi> ſhall not there ariſe to <hi>diſturb</hi> our fancies, and <hi>corrupt</hi> our imaginations, to fill us with <hi>black</hi> and <hi>diſmall</hi> thoughts: <hi>Malevolent Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> ſhall be below us, and have no influence in that <hi>Superior</hi> ſtate. And thus much for what doth conſiſt <hi>In Remotione Malorum, In Removal of what is bad.</hi> Let us now conſider the Second: which conſiſteth</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Exhibitione Bonorum,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring what is Good.</hi> And this I ſuppoſe may be ſumm'd up in three Particulars:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170181:58"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Viſion of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Society with Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Fruition of inconceiveable Joy.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>Viſion of God.</hi> Whilſt we are <hi>in the body,</hi> we are <hi>abſent</hi> from the Lord, he ſtandeth <hi>behinde our wall,</hi> as the expreſſion is, Cant. 2.9. If ever we have a glimpſe of God, it is but when he is pleaſed to look forth at <hi>the windows,</hi> or doth ſhew himſelf through <hi>the lattice;</hi> the Saints do but at beſt ſee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, through a <hi>glaſs darkly</hi> in this life, but then <hi>face to face:</hi> which whether it be <hi>Oculo corporen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Fort. de vidend. Deo, ep. <hi>311</hi> &amp; deinceps Tom. <hi>2. A quin.</hi> Suppl. ad tert. partem quaeſt. <hi>52.</hi> art. <hi>2. 1 Ioh. 3.2.</hi>
                  </note> to me is <hi>curioſity</hi> to inquire, would be <hi>boldneſs</hi> to determine: But cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainly they ſhall ſee him and S. <hi>John</hi> tells us how <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>As he is.</hi> Thoſe bleſſed Saints, who have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on him whom they have not ſeen, ſhall there enjoy their deſired ſight of him whom they have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, according to his prayer, Joh. 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that they alſo
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170181:59"/>whom thou haſt given me, be with me, where I am, that they may behold my glory,</hi> &amp;c. If thoſe eyes were <hi>bleſſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 10.23.</note> which did behold Chriſt in his low eſtate, how happy are they who ſee him ſit at the <hi>right hand</hi> of the Father? Here, he was covered in <hi>Scarlet,</hi> there he is clothed with Honour and Majeſty: Here he was Crowned with <hi>Thorns,</hi> there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with a <hi>Diadem of Glory:</hi> Here a Reed in his hand, there the <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter</hi> of his Kingdome to protect his people; or the <hi>Rod</hi> of his Juſtice, wherewith to daſh in pieces his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: Here ſpit upon, there his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach taken away: Upon the Croſs rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed on, and blaſphemed, there a <hi>Name above every name,</hi> at which <hi>every knee</hi> doth bow: Here invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with <hi>Souldiers,</hi> there encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with Millions of glorious <hi>Saints and Angels,</hi> partakers of that bliſs with him, which he hath purchaſed for, and confirmed them in. The Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> having ſeen God even in <hi>this</hi> life, ſets up a Monument thereof, and calls the place <hi>Peniel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32.30.</note> in token of joy: <hi>For I
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170181:59"/>have ſeen God face to face</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and my life is preſerved.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gerhar. Med. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quod ſi momentanea Dei viſio tantum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit apportare laetitiae cumulum; quid potuit viſio ejus aeterna?</hi> If thoſe beams of comfort which are reflected upon them here,<note place="margin">Domine tu ſcis quod illo die cum talia loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur, &amp; mundus iſte nobis inter verba iſta vileſceret cum omnibus delectationibus ſuis. <hi>Aug. lib. Con. 9. Cant. 504.</hi>
                  </note> do ſo refreſh their Souls in this <hi>valley of tears,</hi> what will be their joy, when the Lord ſhall be their <hi>everlaſting light?</hi> If the Spouſe her bowels are moved when Chriſt puts in his hand by <hi>the hole of the door,</hi> how will her Soul be inflamed, when ſhe her ſelf ſhall be received into thoſe everlaſting <hi>Manſions?</hi> When this <hi>Sun</hi> ariſeth, every <hi>ſhadow</hi> will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear; and he who did ſometimes ſpeak roughly to his people, ſhal then diſcover himſelf to be their Father, and their hearts ſhall <hi>revive</hi> within them. They who did bear his <hi>image</hi> here, when he ſhall appear ſhall be <hi>like him.</hi> They who in the world cried, <hi>Hoſanna to the Higheſt,</hi> ſhall then chant forth <hi>Hallelujah to him that ſitteth upon the Throne.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170181:60"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>The Society of Saints and Angels.</hi> This is another part of their Happineſs. Our Saviour deſcribeth part of Heavens Happineſs to conſiſt therein;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. ad Theod lapſ. Paraen. Luk 13.28, 29. Mat. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall come from the Eaſt and the Weſt, the North and the South, and ſit down with Abraham, Iſaac, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero de Senect. pag. (mibi) <hi>212.</hi>
                  </note> If <hi>Cato</hi> the Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher could comfort himſelf in his old age, with an <hi>O praeclarum diem cum ad illud animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum concilium, caetum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proficiſcar, &amp; cum ex hac turba &amp; colluvione diſcedam!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vid. Melch. Adam. vit. Bullinger. Vid. Ger. Med. <hi>48.</hi> de ſuaviſſima Angelorum in caelo aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatione.</note> And <hi>Socrates</hi> againſt death, becauſe after it he hoped to ſee <hi>Homer, Heſiod,</hi> and other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men. How much more may a <hi>Saint</hi> lay down his head in<note n="*" place="margin">Lu. 2.29. Heb. 12.23.</note> 
                  <hi>peace,</hi> and rejoyce, ſeeing he is but going to the <hi>City of the living God, to the heavenly Jeruſalem, to an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of Angels, to the general aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, which are writien in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170181:60"/>and to the spirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Chry. hom. 70. de mart Egypt.</note> The company of the Saints even in this life, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the weak, encourage the faint, chear up the dejected, whilſt by their mutual intercourſe, and intimate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, they provoke one another to love and good works, inliven each others zeal, incite, and incourage each other by a good example, to <hi>hold forth to the end,</hi> that they may receive the <hi>Crown of Life;</hi> and by mutual offices of love, do endear themſelves one to the other, and chiefly to God, whoſe image they behold ingravened in their Souls, as the bond of that Union which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. If <hi>this</hi> be ſo pleaſant, how ſweet will then their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion be in that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te of peace, where they who ſerved the Lord <hi>with one ſhoulder,</hi> and prayed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether here,<note place="margin">Omnium Chriſtiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum spes (fratre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſimi) in futurum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus extenaitur u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod hic ſervimus Dom no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi nos ſerviſſe lae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. <hi>Aug. in verb. apoſt. 2 Cor. 5.10.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall with one conſent offer up praiſe to their God, where nothing ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt their joy, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their hopes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict their wills, which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170181:61"/>are then perfectly on with God's. O <hi>bleſſed Society,</hi> where is no jarring <hi>envy,</hi> ſtrife! O <hi>heavenly Conſort,</hi> where is no Diſcord, but a perfect <hi>Harmony</hi> with God and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! Me-thinks I could ſay with the Pſalmiſt (his phraſe ſomewhat va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried) Who will give me <hi>the wings of a Dove,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.6.</note> that I may fly hither, and <hi>be at reſt?</hi> And this is the ſecond thing that ſhall be conferr'd upon them; they have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>like unto God</hi> in holineſs here; they ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as with, ſo <hi>like the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> in glory hereafter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Fruition of inconceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Joy.</hi> In this place, and that <hi>to purpoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.8.</note> God ſhall make his people to <hi>hear the voice of joy and gladneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. ad Thcod. lapſ. paraen.</note> If <hi>corn,</hi> and <hi>wine,</hi> and <hi>oil,</hi> do make mens hearts <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> what will the <hi>light of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> when lift upon his people, ſo as never more to be obſcured with a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170181:61"/>frown? God ſhall then <hi>put glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into their hearts:</hi> his joy in this life is in them, then ſhall they <hi>enter into their Maſters joy,</hi> Mat. 25.23. Here it is our happineſs to have God rejoyce over us; there it ſhall be the honour of the Saints, to joy <hi>in</hi> and with <hi>the Lord.</hi> Joy here is in a capacity of <hi>increaſe;</hi> there it ſhall <hi>be full. Jeremiah,</hi> though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times caſt into the dungeon, as not worthy to behold the light, ſhall <hi>ſhine as the Sun;</hi> and though his feet did ſtick in the mire, yet ſhall he <hi>lift up his head for joy. Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> who did ſing in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whilſt their feet were in the Stocks, ſhall then be delivered, and their <hi>glory</hi> ſhall awake to their Redeemers praiſe: Then <hi>the eyes of the blinde ſhall be opend, and the ears of the deaf ſhall be unſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; then ſhall the lame man leap as an Hart, and the tongue of the dumb ſhall ſing: In the wilderneſs ſhall waters break out, and the ſtreams in the deſart,</hi> Iſa. 15.5, 6. This is the Saints <hi>Nuptial</hi> day;<note place="margin">Rev. 19.7.</note> ſhould they not ſing for mirth?
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170181:62"/>The accompliſhment of their <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare;</hi> ſhall they not be in peace? The <hi>Harveſt</hi> of their Hopes; ſhould they not now rejoyce, who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are gathered into the garner? Yes ſurely: But how great ſhall be the meaſure thereof? Which leads me to the third Conſideration;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quoad Menſuram, The Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their joy.</hi> Of the<note n="*" place="margin">Quae ſententia plus habet disputationis quam certitudinis &amp; utilitatis. <hi>Muſcul. in 1 Cor. 15.40.</hi>
                  </note> different Degrees of which, there are more <hi>nice</hi> Diſcourſes, than <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory</hi> Reſolutions: Some, whilſt they would engroſs a greater portion of this glory, may poſſibly detract from Gods grace, which is free, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows a <hi>penny</hi> upon him who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the <hi>laſt hour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quo uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> denario vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aeterna. <hi>Aug. Exp. in Johan.</hi>
                  </note> as well as on them who did <hi>bear the heat and burthen of the day.</hi> The <hi>Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> is moſt believed, becauſe chiefly deſired, and is an excellent motive to be <hi>abundant in the work of the Lord,</hi> becauſe he that <hi>ſoweth ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly,</hi> ſhall <hi>reap</hi> alſo ſo: but the<note n="†" place="margin">Vide Pet. Mart. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>15.40.</hi> Muſc. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Negative</hi> is not yet beyond diſpute.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170181:62"/>
               <p>The various<note n="*" place="margin">Has diſſimilitude in reſurrectione mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum apparet verum in applicatione vulge crratur, &amp;c. <hi>Calv. in 1 Cor. 15.41.</hi>
                  </note> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the <hi>Stars,</hi> is an Argument wanting <hi>light</hi> to evidence the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent glory of the Saints; it being wreſted from the firſt intention of the Apoſtle: and, which is more, ſeems to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the <hi>Lord of Glory;</hi> who ſpeaking <hi>indefinitely</hi> of the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.43.</note> they <hi>ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father</hi> And it may ſeem a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, That each Saint ſhould be<note n="†" place="margin">Luk. 20.36.</note> 
                  <hi>equal to the Angels,</hi> and yet <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal amongst themſelves</hi> in this ſtate of Bliſs, unleſs we alſo averre <hi>different Orders</hi> amongſt them:<note n="⸪" place="margin">Vid. Wal. hanc opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem, cap. de Aug. off. p. <hi>198.</hi>
                  </note> Which is but to allow a <hi>Scruple</hi> in the Schools; and that eaſier to aſſert, than maintain, rather than <hi>Reſolve a Doubt</hi> in our own breſts. As for that Similitude of the Sun, being more obvious to the<note n="‥" place="margin">Bellar. de aeter. faelic. ſanct. l. <hi>5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eagles eye,</hi> than to other Birds; or the fire its diverſe heat, operating in a ſeveral manner upon many perſon: Whatever this may <hi>clear,</hi> yet it doth not neceſſarily prove this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170181:63"/>If I were to give my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I had rather<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Wal. optimè diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerentem de hac re tit. de Eccleſ: trium, pag. <hi>451.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Affirm,</hi> though (I ſay nor) there is probable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to deny this Aſſertion: But <hi>cautious Ignorance,</hi> is better than <hi>raſh Preſumption;</hi> therefore I leave this as I found it, <hi>An Exerciſe</hi> of our knowledge, and not by my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, to be <hi>determined</hi> as an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> of our Faith. But to ſpeak more ſtrictly to the Meaſure of this Glory, I have told you it is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the firſt-fruits thereof in this life, calls it <hi>joy unspeakable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and full of glory.</hi> It is ſtyled, <hi>fulneſs of joy,</hi> Pſal. 16.11. Glorious objects to the eye, do uſually affect the heart with <hi>joyful admiration:</hi> and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath deſcribed the City of God by ſuch things, as are moſt affecting to ſenſe, that ſo we may ſee the inconceiveable worth of that eſtate of Bliſs; and by our neceſſity of Divine Condeſcention in this particular, gueſs at the <hi>Jewel,</hi> by the beauty of the <hi>Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net;</hi> and have a tranſient view of the condition of the Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170181:63"/>by conſidering the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> deſcending thence from God. We ſee this City deſcribed, Rev. 21.16. and whatſoever is glorious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in it. If <hi>for defence,</hi> it hath a <hi>Wall,</hi> and that not of Clay, but of <hi>Jasper,</hi> the foundation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is garniſh'd with <hi>all manner of Precious ſtones.</hi> If <hi>for Beauty,</hi> even the ſtreets are of <hi>pure gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 4.10</note> like <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Chariot, the <hi>midſt</hi> thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>paved with love.</hi> Thus God hath <hi>revealed</hi> Truth in a Myſtery, uttered Knowledge in Parables; and what our underſtanding doth not compriſe, our ſenſes by this deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption may apprehend of that eſtate.<note place="margin">Semper nobis in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem veniat aeterne fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas de cujus excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſi omnia dicta fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint quibus omnium ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum linguae ſufficiant vix tamen infima cjus particula delibata fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Calv. inſtit. l. 4. c. 25.</hi>
                  </note> Let us then be contented to admire, what we cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; to believe, what we cannot concelve; to conſider, what no tongue can expreſs. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems at a loſs for words to expreſs his thoughts of this glory, he ſtyles it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Cor. 4.17. Which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170181:64"/>phraſe, though we reade, <hi>A far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> Yet Interpreters are at a loſs to explain it. Judge we then of that good land, by the <hi>Grapes</hi> which are brought from <hi>Eſchol;</hi> of the excellency of the Honey, by its taſte upon the <hi>end of the Rod.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chryſ. ad Theod. lapſ. Parae.</note> Have we ever diſcourſed with one who did lie in the boſom of God, who hath eaten of the <hi>hidden Manna,</hi> and to whom God hath given the <hi>White ſtone,</hi> and did not ſuch a ones <hi>face ſhine,</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by his ſpeech we might know he was upon the <hi>Confines</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem?</hi> Or have any of our Spirits been wounded with our Tranſgreſſions; and hath the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> afterwards riſen upon us <hi>with heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his wings?</hi> The tempe of a mans Spirit in ſuch a caſe, is ſome <hi>dark Repreſentation</hi> of that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joy. Yet this is but the <hi>twilight</hi> of Glory, the <hi>dawning</hi> of that Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Day. Nay, whilſt we are
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170181:64"/>
                  <hi>speaking</hi> hereof, ſhould God open the <hi>windows of Heaven,</hi> and give us a <hi>Steven's-ſight</hi> of himſelf in Bliſs, ſet us upon <hi>Mount Nebo,</hi> that we might behold this <hi>Land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;</hi> though this would <hi>ſtrengthen our weak hands, confirm our feeble knees,</hi> and encourage us in our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel to that <hi>Reſt</hi> which <hi>remaineth;</hi> and, with <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Chryſoſt. ad Theod. lapſ. Paraen. in verba Pet. Mart. 17.41.</note> conſtrain us to ſay, <hi>Lord, it is good for us to be here:</hi> yet this would but be as the <hi>Gate of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> our entrance would not be, till with him we fell aſleep. We finde Gods people ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation hereof, rapt up in an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie</hi> of heavenly joy, with their <hi>believing</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it; <hi>whiſpering forth</hi> what they underſtood, or <hi>rather</hi> were ignorant of, concerning Heaven, in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170181:65"/>that of the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 31.19. <hi>O how great is thy goodneſs, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee!</hi> How happy are they, whoſe Souls do <hi>lodge in goodneſs!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 25.13.</note> whoſe action is reflection upon by-paſt Miſery, to rejoyce becauſe of its then being fled away! whoſe labour is turned into <hi>leiſure</hi> to praiſe their God! to whom no evil <hi>ſhall appear,</hi> no good <hi>be hid,</hi> when God ſhall be to them all in all! Men look upon Religion, uſually as a <hi>Scare-Crow;</hi> and upon the Profeſſors thereof, as ſo many <hi>Ghoſts</hi> or <hi>Walking ſhadows:</hi> but were they not ignorant of this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joy, with which <hi>a ſtranger intermedleth not,</hi> they would then forſake their fading pleaſures, and, with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> chooſe to <hi>ſuffer affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the people of God,</hi> rather than to glut themſelves with the moſt ſatiating contents of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which are <hi>but for a ſeaſon.</hi> Yea, did Gods people live under deep impreſſions of thoſe noble and lovely thoughts, wherewith God hath expreſt himſelf concerning this their Bliſs, their Souls would be
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170181:65"/>drawn after him with that vigour and activity, that the heavy Iron is by the Loadſtone: They would then no longer queſtion, ſuſpect Gods willingneſs to entertain them, but bathe their Souls in that <hi>Abyſs</hi> of Love; caſt their ſelves into thoſe Arms that are <hi>ſtretched out</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. This <hi>purer</hi> joy would cauſe them to diſreliſh the <hi>fleeting</hi> pleaſures, wherewith Satan doth bait his hook, and allure them to Tranſgreſſion. <hi>Stupefied</hi> Reaſon, and <hi>inchanted</hi> Senſe, are the onely Caterers of earthly joy: but the Sons of God derive their comfort from a more noble Spring. The World, as it cannot take away, neither can it give that <hi>peace</hi> which they <hi>inherit</hi> from him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.27</note> who is ſtyled, <hi>The Everlaſting Father,</hi> and,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The Prince</hi> thereof. No wonder then, if the <hi>pious Father</hi> doth rather confeſs his ignorance,<note place="margin">Quanta erit illa fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas? ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio. <hi>Aug. de civ. Dei l. 22. c. 30.</hi>
                  </note> than endevour a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the greatneſs of that Heavenly joy. Me-thinks, when we poor Mortals do hear of this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible Crown,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25.</note> this <hi>inacceſſible Light,</hi> this <hi>immortal Life,</hi> we ſhould
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170181:66"/>ſtretch every Nerve, intend our ſtrength, be <hi>unwearied</hi> in the work of the Lord, caſt a <hi>deſpiſing eye</hi> upon the <hi>withering</hi> beauty of this <hi>inferiour</hi> World; run <hi>the race which is ſet before us;</hi> reſiſt <hi>unto blood;</hi> fight the good <hi>fight of faith,</hi> that ſo, if by any means we might <hi>lay hold on Eternal Life:</hi> Which brings me to the laſt Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quoad Durationem, Its Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> It is called in the Text <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> We ſay of the things of this life <hi>(though in another ſenſe)</hi> The End doth <hi>Crown</hi> the Work;<note place="margin">Finis coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat opus.<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Pet. 5.4.</note> the Event doth prove the Action: But this is the <hi>Crown</hi> of this <hi>Eſtate,</hi> that it is <hi>incircled</hi> with Eternity. This Epithite, <hi>It is Mortal,</hi> doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace all <hi>Sublunary</hi> Glory; the thought thereof leaves a <hi>bitterneſs</hi> in our choiceſt earthly comforts; it cauſeth our <hi>Sun</hi> to <hi>ſet at Noon:</hi> but it is not thus in Heaven; <hi>Their Sun ſhall no more go down, neither ſhall their Mooon withdraw it ſelf: for the Lord ſhall be their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting light, and the dayes of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170181:66"/>their mourning ſhall be ended,</hi> Iſa. 60.20. When they are thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in that ſtate of Bliſs, then ſhall they ſing that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Return unto thy reſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 116.</note> 
                  <hi>O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee: for thou haſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered my ſoul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling;</hi> whilſt the wicked ſhall <hi>ſee it, and be grieved; he ſhall gnaſh with his teeth, and melt away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have you ſeen a <hi>Glimpſe</hi> of this <hi>Approaching Glory.</hi> And poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſome, whoſe hearts are affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, may with him, Mat. 19.6. ask, <hi>What good thing ſhall I do, that I may have Eternal Life?</hi> I ſhall ſend ſuch a one no further than our Saviours anſwer, ver. 17. <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandments:</hi> for to them that <hi>obey</hi> him,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Hom. 25. de fut. jud. tom. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Eternal Salvation.</hi> Or let us look a little more, and ſee the condition of our admiſſion hither; or for the default of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170181:67"/>what we ſhall be hindred this place of Happineſs: Joh. 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born again of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> It is our <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth,</hi> which will uſher in this <hi>New-life:</hi> and this ſuppoſed, there are ſeveral graces, which, if they be <hi>in us, and abound,</hi> will <hi>miniſter</hi> unto us an <hi>entrance abundantly</hi> into the <hi>everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And they are theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Humility.</hi> The Saints of God do not onely grow as the Lilly, the moſt tall and comely Flower in the Garden, but caſt forth their roots as <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.5.</note> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Chryſoſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 27. de profec. Evan. tom. 5.</note> Humility is their way to honour. I never ſee a ſtrong Caſtle, a fair Tower, but its foundation was laid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding deep; whereas a Cottage may ſtand on the <hi>Surface</hi> of the earth: neither was there ever any one made a <hi>Temple</hi> for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> a <hi>fit Habitation for God,</hi> through the Spirit, who was not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170181:67"/>firſt deeply humbled. Whereas the <hi>Devils Sty,</hi> the heart of a wicked man, may be proud, and lifted up. But let ſuch a one top the Stars, yet thence God will pull him down, and <hi>trample</hi> upon his glory: But he who is <hi>poor</hi> in Spirit, is upon the firſt Round in <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, the top whereof reacheth unto Heaven. <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are ſuch, for <hi>theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.3.</note> it is theirs now in Reverſion, it ſhall be theirs hereafter in Poſſeſſion. Our <hi>Saviour,</hi> when born, did lie in a Manger; and now he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted on the right hand of God; he delighteth to dwell with him, who is of an <hi>humble and contrite spirit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 24.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended from the Croſs unto the Crown; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſhame, before he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his glory; was found in the <hi>form of a Servant,</hi> before his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing declared the <hi>Son of God:</hi> and we muſt <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>humble our ſelves under his mighty hand,</hi> if we expect to be <hi>exalted</hi> in his <hi>due time.</hi> God will <hi>teach the humble;</hi> and ſuch whom he
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170181:68"/>
                  <hi>guideth</hi> by his <hi>Counſel</hi> now, he will afterwards <hi>bring</hi> unto his <hi>Glory:</hi> This is the <hi>firſt duty</hi> we ſhould practiſe in order to our future Bliſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Purity</hi> in Heart, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in a holy life.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God:</hi> But there ſhall in <hi>no wiſe</hi> enter into the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> any <hi>unclean thing,</hi> or <hi>that defileth,</hi> Revel. 21.27. If Heaven were an <hi>Eliſium,</hi> the proud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might perhaps get in, under the notion of an Heroick Spirit: If it were a <hi>Turkiſh Paradiſe,</hi> the unclean perſon might thruſt in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the crowd. But this eſtate is nothing ſuch.<note place="margin">Pſa. 93.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Holineſs becometh thy houſe,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi> much more then doth it become theſe <hi>everlaſting habitations.</hi> This pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of heart, is that which maketh the Saints <hi>meet,</hi> to be <hi>partakers</hi> of this everlaſting Inheritance: It makes Heaven a <hi>ſutable good</hi> to the deſires of their immortal Souls. <hi>Fleſh and Blood</hi> in its degenerate eſtate,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>cannot enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170181:68"/>of God;</hi> even the <hi>hope</hi> of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with him, doth call upon us to purifie our ſelves as <hi>he is pure,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, Love;</hi> to which might be annexed <hi>Peace,</hi> its iſſue: He that liveth in Love, <hi>God dwelleth in him;</hi> He that abideth in peace,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>videbit &amp;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pax. vide Heb</hi> 7.2.</note> ſhall live in the <hi>viſion of peace</hi> for evermore. A Soul <hi>wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> with Love, will fly more ſwiftly to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt. Hom. 57. de Poenit. 9.</note> and finde ſpeedy Admiſſion thereinto: Love doth conform us to God now; and they who are like him here, when he is manifeſted, ſhall be <hi>with him</hi> where he is. Yet God expects this Love ſhould appear to others by the fruits thereof; and becauſe our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>extends</hi> not unto him, we ſhould ſhew it to the <hi>excellent ones in the earth.</hi> There is a work and <hi>labour</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> ſhew'd by miniſtring unto the Saints, which we ſee the Judge of the World
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170181:69"/>taking notice of,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. Hom. 25. de Poen. 5. Tom. 1. in Matth. 25.31.</note> and requiting, Matth. 25.35, 36. They who do ſuch works <hi>in ſecret,</hi> ſhall certainly eat of the <hi>Hidden Manna:</hi> He whoſe <hi>left hand</hi> knoweth not what his <hi>right hand</hi> doth,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.32</note> ſhall not ſtand on the <hi>left hand,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall ſever the wicked from the juſt. He who ſoundeth not <hi>a Trumpet</hi> to gain the praiſe of men, ſhall be rewarded openly, and receive praiſe from God. The poor man's <hi>Box</hi> will prove the ſafeſt <hi>Cheſt,</hi> wherein to hide our Treaſure: Giving to him, is to beſtow on our ſelves; yea, to <hi>lend to the Lord,</hi> who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay with the greateſt intereſt. The Prophet ſpeaking of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Iſa. 46.6. tells us, <hi>They la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh gold out of the bag, and weigh ſilver in the balance:</hi> but when the Idol is framed, yet can he not <hi>anſwer,</hi> or <hi>ſave out of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> But there is a better way to thrive, which he takes notice of; namely, To <hi>draw out our Soul to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170181:69"/>the hungry, to ſatisfie the afflicted ſoul, to bring the poor that are caſt out, to ones houſe:</hi> They that do thus,<note place="margin">1 Tim 6.19.</note> 
                  <hi>lay up in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, Patient enduring Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction</hi> for the Name of Chriſt. This is that which doth make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion even now honourable in the world, whilſt thoſe who do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, do flouriſh like the <hi>Palm,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe weights of ſorrow which are daily caſt upon them by the ungrateful World, with whom for a time they do converſe. Like their <hi>Saviour,</hi> their honour doth moſt ſhine forth, whilſt their enemies ſeek the moſt to eclipſe their fame; much more ſhall this advance their worth, when God ſhall make their reproach to vaniſh, their ſhame to diſappear. Upon ſuch the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>of Glory reſteth</hi> here,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14</note> and they ſhall <hi>reſt in Glory</hi> hereafter. The Apoſtle doubts not to call this <hi>an evident token of Salvation, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170181:70"/>that of God,</hi> Phil. 1.24. and tells believers, <hi>That their light Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not onely work, but <hi>work out a farre more exceeding, and eternal weight of Glory,</hi> with the which they are not to be compared. This is that which is the great ſupport of their Souls, in their <hi>fiery trials,</hi> the <hi>Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſs with their ſpirits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> 
                  <hi>If ſo be that they ſuffer with him, they ſhall be alſo glorified together.</hi> The <hi>Lilly</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall no longer then be amongſt the <hi>Thorns;</hi> his <hi>Dove,</hi> which hath here lyen amongſt <hi>the pots,</hi> ſhall have her wings <hi>covered with ſilver,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 68.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and her feathers with yellow gold.</hi> Thus the Lord ſhall bring back the <hi>Captivity of his people,</hi> ſo that <hi>Judah ſhall be glad, and Iſrael ſhall rejoyce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AWAKE</hi> then, <hi>OH</hi> my Soul! load not thy ſelf with <hi>Refined</hi> Clay, trample upon theſe <hi>Earthly Nothings:</hi> Admire not thoſe <hi>Apples of Sodom,</hi> which though beautiful to the Eye, yet when
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170181:70"/>thou toucheſt them, moulder in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to duſt; Gaze not upon theſe <hi>glittering</hi> Pleaſures, <hi>colour'd</hi> Griefs, <hi>bluſhing</hi> Woes; Reliſh not theſe <hi>ſugred</hi> Lies, but account <hi>Heaven</hi> thy Happineſs, <hi>Godlineſs</hi> thy Crown, <hi>Chriſt</hi> thy All: So ſhalt thou <hi>inſult over death,</hi> have <hi>bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in the day of Judgement, ſhalt not be <hi>left in Hall,</hi> thy <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall go before thee, the Glory of the Lord ſhall be thy rereward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>TH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> have I finiſhed my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations on theſe <hi>Laſt Things;</hi> beſeeching him who is the <hi>Prince of Life,</hi> to prepare us for the <hi>Approach of Death;</hi> Him who ſhall be our <hi>Judge,</hi> that he will be our <hi>Advocate;</hi> Him who hath the <hi>Keyes of the Bottomleſs Pit,</hi> that he would <hi>ſhut the mouth of the Grave,</hi> that it may not devour us; Him who is gone before to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a place for his people,</hi> that he would <hi>prepare us</hi> for that place, where we may bear a part in the heavenly <hi>Chorus,</hi> and ſing that <hi>new
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170181:71"/>Song,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Bleſſing, honour, glory, and power be unto him that ſitteth on the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis alius noſter eſt Finis;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de civ. Dei, l. 21. c. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>niſi pervenire ad Regnum, eujus nullus eſt</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS?</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:71"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Ingenuous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe, with ſome other faults that do oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in the words or pointing, as they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thy candid Cenſure, ſo alſo beg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ingenuous Correction, The Authors abſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and the Printers miſtake, being the cauſe of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Page</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line</cell>
                     <cell role="label">For</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Reade</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>which</cell>
                     <cell>that which</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>Boren.</cell>
                     <cell>Beren.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>hath</cell>
                     <cell>have</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>interitus</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>introitus</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>heart</cell>
                     <cell>hearts</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>hath</cell>
                     <cell>had</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>illa</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ille</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>topice</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>tropice</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>tabernable</cell>
                     <cell>tabernacle</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Pſal. 29.7.</cell>
                     <cell>21.9.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>103</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>106</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>115</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>Mart.</cell>
                     <cell>Mat.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>mar.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:72"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Januarii</hi> 12, 1657.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR <hi>Cantabrigiae,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Theoph. Dillingham <hi>Procan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ri. Minſhull.</item>
                     <item>Ra. Cudworth.</item>
                     <item>Guil. Dillingham.</item>
                     <item>John Arrowſmith.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170181:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
